<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gear | StevenHorner.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/categories/gear/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-19T17:07:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Horner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Water]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/09/11/water/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-11T16:15:20+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/09/11/water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Ullswater-Doris-049.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Water the single most important thing to us humans. You could get away without shelter or food for several days or weeks but not so for water. Supposedly we can last 3 days without water, but long before that you would experience headaches, probably dizziness and obviously a total lack of energy. Even though it's so important many of us backpackers don't give it much thought or we just do what we've always done.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I like the idea that each time you go on a trip you should try something new and I have experimented over the last year or two trying to gauge how much water to carry depending on the environment and the expected weather conditions. Below is a shortened summary showing how my usage has changed (top oldest).</p>

<p><strong>Day Walks </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>1L Flask of tea &amp; 500ml orange juice</li>
<li>2 x 500ml water bottle</li>
<li>1 x 500ml water bottle &amp; Kuksa</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Overnighter </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>2L Camelbak, Sigg bottle &amp; 1lLPlatypus for camp</li>
<li>2 x 500ml water bottle &amp; 1L Platypus for camp</li>
<li>1 x 500ml water bottle, Kuksa &amp; 1L Platypus for camp</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_123407.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>There can be huge differences in the volume of water needed for a trip, I've had several trips where I have got it wrong, going back several years. One that comes to mind was walking the Wainwrights around Ennerdale, after a wildcamp on Haystacks I filled the 2L Camelbak and the 500ml <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Sigg_Traveller_60cl_Water_Bottle_271-1753.html">SIG bottle</a> before setting off. The day turned out to be hot and back in 2007 I was carrying a lot more in my pack than today, after walking over Brandreth, Green Gable, Great Gable, Kirk Fell, Pillar, Scoat Fell, Steeple and Haycock I had run out of water and hadn't realised how low the water level had become due to the Camelbak being hidden in the pack. There was no water up high and I was feeling the effects, very sluggish, headaches and I just wanted to sit down. On this occassion I checked the map and made a detour to Silver cove and found a stream thankfully bubbling away. I was in the lake district beneath me was Ennerdale which I obviously could of headed for. I had an added problem on this trip, this was probably the first occassion when I began to notice I had a heart problem and just wanted to lie down and sleep, the water problem just made it worse.</p>

<p>I had other occassions when I ran out of water on day walks due to not knowing how much water was remaining in the camelbak. On one of these the pipes froze in winter, you can get insulated pipes which the person I was walking with had, theirs froze too. This was the end of using reservoirs hidden in my pack. Something that could be worth a look is the new <a href="http://www.camelbak.com/Sports-Recreation/Accessories/Flowmeter.aspx">flow meter</a> from Camelbak which has a display that lets you know how much water is remaining among other information. I find looking at a clear bottle much simpler and cheaper. I find turning a water bottle upside down in winter prevents the opening freezing, water freezes from the top down.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Fullscreen-capture-11092011-132336.bmp.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> I have never treated water with any form of filter, tablet or any other method. This is likely due to the areas I choose to walk being mountainous and/or remote. Although I have walked with people who spent 10 minutes filtering water through an inline filter while I stood there scooping water with my Kuksa and drinking it. This was a from a fast moving stream in the North York Moors. Some may think I am stupid but I try to choose a source of water that hopefully wouldn't be contaminated, I have never been ill. If I walked through more urban areas or lots of flat farmed areas I may think differently.</p>

<p> This is my personal choice, I've seen many walkers carry 5+ litres of water in the Lake District or Scotland and never need to stop to fill up. They generally do need to stop due to carrying 5+kg of water weight on their backs though. I mentioned earlier its the skill of judging what water maybe available, clearly if you are walking in hot dry areas or polluted ares of the world you will NEED to carry much more water.</p>

<p> Two of my favourite pieces of kit are my Kuksa and Platypus, the Kuksa I bought while on a trip to Finland and was introdused to them by <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com">Hendrik Morkel</a>. Since then it is attached to my pack on every trip I make. It's not just used for taking pictures on summits, it's main use is to scoop water whenever I pass a stream. You could use a far lighter plastic cup but it's just not the same as a carved wooden kuksa. The 1L platypus is one of those bits of kit that is just so simple you give it no thought. It rolls up to nothing and sits in the very top of my pack waiting until the last water point of the day where I will fill it up for my camp water.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_121908.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> I've used the same platypus for the last 4-5 years and it has never leaked or developed any problems. <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/">Webtogs</a> asked if I wanted to test a hydration system a couple of months ago, I already had this post in mind so asked for another <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus/">Playtpus</a>. I could of chosen a more expensive <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Camelbak/">Camelbak</a> but I prefer the simple system I've developed. I received the <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser </a>which features a pipe so you can hide the bladder in your pack and drink using the bite valve without having to do a strange yoga stretching position to remove a bottle from your pack side pockets. The bite valve isn't as nice as Camelbaks but it works, having said Camelbaks are better I dislike the newer style shut off valve on Camelbaks. Their old valve was far easier to operate one handed. The <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a> doesn't feature a shut valve, this could be a problem as the bite valve becomes old and water seeps out but I haven't used it for long enough. An <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Shutoff_Valve_101435.html">upgraded valve</a> is available as an upgrade.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Skitched-image0-600x438.png" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_154924.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> The <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a> features a very simple clip that allows you to attach the pipe to your pack or clothes, I would remove it though as its a bit unnescessary most packs have loops you can easily push the bite valve into rather than using the extra metal clip.</p>

<p> I already mentioned that I decided I no longer want to use a water reservoir with pipes, be it a camelbak or a <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a> due to finding it hard to track how much water I was drinking and how much is remaining. So why ask for a <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a>, I wanted the main reservoir not the pipe and may on future trips abroad use an inline filter to fill up my other water containers. The Platypus has changed slightly since I bought my original years ago. The new ones are made of slightly less rigid plastic, have a loop to either hang or pick it up by and the entry/exit to the platypus is now on the corner. Having the entry/exit on the corner makes sense if you are using it in a hydration system, all the water will be funneled towards the pipe due the shape of the reservoir. Camelbak pipes exit near the centre at the bottom and the last bit of water can be hard to suck through. Camelbaks also have seperate fill up/pipe exits giving 2 possible points of failure rather than the 1 on the Platypus.</p>

<p> The only criticism I would have of the Platypus is they can take considerably longer to fill due to the small simple top. The Hoser doesn't come with a standard cap like my old one, because it is intended to be used with the pipe and bite valve. Most bottle tops from fizzy drinks containers do fit though or you could buy some <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Closure_Cap__pack_of_two__101432.html">official closure caps</a> from Platypus. As well as a criticism, it is also an advantage, keeping it incredibly simple is one less thing to go wrong. Several times I've struggled to remove the large opening cap from Camelbaks when they have stuck, almost breaking my thumbs to open them, slight exageration but it hurt. Platypus may of already of answered this with their Big Zip but Keep It Simple Stupid (Kiss) comes to mind with less to go wrong and leak I will stick to my current system.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_155016.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> So to summarise my water system for walking in the British mountains: I always carry my Kuksa to drink whenever I pass a stream or other water source, 1 or 2 500ml clear water bottles and a <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">1L Platypus</a> minus the hose/pipe for camp at night or for when water maybe scarce at higher levels during the day. This isn't really a review of the Platypus there's not much to review and the best recommendation is I asked for another over several other more expensive fancy systems.</p>

<p> <strong>Gear Mentioned</strong></p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Platypus 1L Hoser</a> = £15.99 (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Sigg_Traveller_60cl_Water_Bottle_271-1753.html">Sigg 60cl Traveller</a> = £14.99 (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Closure_Cap__pack_of_two__101432.html">Platypus Closure Caps x2</a> = £3.99 (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Shutoff_Valve_101435.html">Platypus Shutoff Valve</a> = (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/products/catalog?q=camelbak+antidote&amp;hl=en&amp;prmd=ivns&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.&amp;biw=1280&amp;bih=909&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;tbm=shop&amp;cid=4745813139539568444&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=RsFsTp_KFYbm-gaexoz2BA&amp;ved=0CF8Q8wIwAQ">Camelbank Reservoir</a> - £21 (Best Price)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/products/catalog?q=camelbak+flow+meter&amp;hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;tbm=shop&amp;cid=6445640845516168167&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hcFsTvK3OtCN-wabnbXvBA&amp;ved=0CFMQ8wIwAA">Camelbak Flow Meter</a> = £16 (Best Price)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/search?q=kuksa&amp;hl=en&amp;tbm=shop&amp;aq=f">Kuksa</a> = £22 (Best price) 500ml water bottle = Free use one someone is throwing out</li>
</ul>


<p> I would be interested in other peoples water systems and what they use, please let me know in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keen A86 Trail Runners Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/04/28/keen-a86-trail-runners-review/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-28T19:30:25+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/04/28/keen-a86-trail-runners-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110402_125935.jpg" alt="Keen A86 Trail Runners" /></p>

<p><strong>Price:</strong> £67.49
<strong>Weight:</strong> 238g (UK 8.5) - my scales
<strong>Product Link:</strong> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Keen_Mens_A86_TR_Trail_Runners_102848-22942.html">Webtogs</a></p>

<p>I was asked by <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/">Webtogs</a> if I would like to review some Keen shoes and to be honest I was going to say No. I own a pair of Keen boots and some slippers which are comfy, but they have thick soles and are what I'm generally trying to get away from to improve my gait (see <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1406">previous post</a>). As I was thinking about how to say No politely, I remembered seeing some pictures of some very lightweight Trail runners announced a couple of months ago. Damn pleased I checked the website first.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The A86s are a big change for Keen, the brand is normally easily identifiable due to the big toe bumpers and large cushioned soles. The A86 are also easily identifiable as Keen footwear but in this case due to the huge brand name on the side.</p>

<p>These are very light (238g per shoe in UK 8.5). I was walking out the door wearing a pair of Montrail Continental Divides for the last time before sending them to their shoe grave when the postman arrived with the A86s. I quickly ditched the Montrails and the weight difference and feel was unbelievable. I'm sure I've got some thick socks that feel heavier. These are the most comfortable shoes I've ever slipped onto my feet. They make you want to run, which I did several times carrying a full pack (a lightweight one obviously).</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110402_130147.jpg" alt="Keen A86 TR" /></p>

<p><strong>Fit</strong></p>

<p>The A86s unlike some other makes, don't feel like I'm wearing clown shoes and my feet have a bit more room in the toe box than Inov-8 212s which feel longer and slightly narrower. Those crazy curved laces aren't just for show, they do an excellent job of fitting the shoe snugly to your foot, yet never feel like they are gripping too tight. The heel cup grips firmly giving you confidence without being uncomfortable.</p>

<p><strong>Grips</strong></p>

<p>The grips can be best described as odd, from pictures it's hard to get a sense of how they actually look. They are not flat circles but are angled (side photos are better for illustration). Keen call it "the dot matrix, multidirectional 3 mm traction lugs" This should allow them to cut into the ground. I was very dubious at first and on my initial walk I found the grips completely covered and clogged with mud but to be fair this would of happened to all but the most aggressive soles. On every other surface that day, grass, gravel, dirt track etc there were no issues. To test the grips further I decided to have a wander along Striding Edge, not somewhere you want to slip. No matter how hard I tried they never failed me, until I came to a nice scree run off Catstye Cam. In comparison to my partners boots these were like a fly in a spiders web, sticking to the ground.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110402_130959.jpg" alt="Oh No they might get muddy" /></p>

<p>After my initial skepticism I've been impressed, although the last few weeks have been very dry and I've had no real opportunity to test on wet rock.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Footwear-and-Weardale-Skyline-beta-026.jpg" alt="Slight wear" /></p>

<p>The angled design of the grips presents a narrow edge to the ground which is going to wear quite quickly on harder surfaces. I can see the edges have worn very slightly after the 60+ miles I've done in them.</p>

<p><strong>Uppers</strong></p>

<p>The uppers are made of very fine mesh which you can see through if you hold them up to the light. This is excellent for ventilation which has been needed on recent trips. This also allows for very quick drying when crossing streams. There's also minimal toe protecting with small toe bumpers and thicker material to prevent toe bashing (I had no problems on Striding Edge). Strangely Keens website says "Weather: Wet - water resistant". They can't have any lining I can see straight through them. Oh that mesh does let quite a bit of dust in the shoes, my feet were black.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Footwear-and-Weardale-Skyline-beta-0211.jpg" alt="Keen A86 Trail Runners" /></p>

<p><strong>Design</strong></p>

<p>The design may not be to everyone tastes, they do shout "Look At Me". Shoes are the few items of clothing that I tend to choose quite loud colours, my <a href="http://www.inov-8.com/Products-Detail.asp?PG=PG1&amp;L=26&amp;P=5050973079">OROC Banana shoes</a> are a perfect example. I really love the design and there are 4 to choose from, although most UK shops only have 2 (the best ones). I wore them one night to the pub and they didn't look out of place. <a href="http://www.keenfootwear.com/product/ss11/shoes/men/trailhead/a86%20tr/classic%20blue!keen%20yellow">Keens website</a> lets you see what they look like with different coloured jeans!</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Striding-Edge-Swirral-Edge-April-2011-085.jpg" alt="Keen A86 gripping on Swirral Edge" /></p>

<p><strong>Pros:</strong> very light, glove like fit, looks <BR>
<strong>Cons:</strong> grips may wear quickly?</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>The best way to sum up my feelings about the A86s is to mention they have caused me a huge dilemma. I was all ready to do my forthcoming <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1393">Highland ZigZag walk</a> in my trusty Terrocs but the A86s feel so comfortable that I'm really struggling to make a decision. I do need to mention that I am used to walking in lightweight shoes and if you jump into these from a pair of big Scarpa boots you may find feeling the ground uncomfortable at first. These are now picked as my first choice shoes when going out walking. I will buy another pair when these eventually do wear out (hopefully not for some time)</p>

<p>You really need to try these on, take advantage of Wegtogs 365 days return policy. I doubt you will want to return them &lt;-- They didn't ask me to say any of this, I genuinely love their service and <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/help/Why_Buy_From_Webtogs.html">policies</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Footwear Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/04/25/footwear-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-25T19:48:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/04/25/footwear-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Footwear-and-Weardale-Skyline-beta-011.jpg" alt="Footwear" /></p>

<p>I'm currently testing a couple of pairs of minimalist shoes and while I was laid in the garden I had the idea to pull out all the footwear I've walked in over the last few years. Sadly I threw out a couple of pairs of boots last year.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The black boots at the top left I never actually used in the hills but are similar to the boots I used for several years. The missing boots were the ones you used to see outside the Famous Army Stores named after places in the lake district.</p>

<p>Footwear in the picture:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Generic steel toe capped boots</strong></li>
<li><strong>Aldi Boots</strong> -- Walked Ben Nevis in these a few years ago</li>
<li><strong>Caterpiller trail shoes</strong></li>
<li><strong>Montrail Continental Divides</strong> -- My first real foray into lightweight footwear</li>
<li><strong>Inov-8 310</strong> -- 5 years old and I still run in these</li>
<li><strong>Inov-8 345</strong> -- Old model, my only GoreTex lines shoes bought for Val d'isere (use for work now)</li>
<li><strong>Inov-8 Terroc 330</strong> -- My main walking shoe, insides dropped to bits</li>
<li><strong>Keen Taarghee II</strong> -- Bought for winter walking with Kahtoolas but prefer shoes now</li>
<li><strong>Merrell Continuums?</strong> -- These cut my feet to bits</li>
<li><strong>Inov-8 Terroc 33</strong>0 -- Another pair</li>
<li><strong>Inov-8 Orroc 340</strong> -- Spiky shoes, fab grip in the winter</li>
<li><strong>Keen A86</strong> -- Very light (currently testing)</li>
<li><strong>Merrell True Glove</strong> -- Barefoot shoes with 0mm drop (currently testing)</li>
</ul>


<p>My footwear journey from heavy boots to lightweight trail runners is perfectly captured in the top picture. Along the way I've had various knee problems and have worn custom made insoles. The Podiatrist described my feet as the worst he had seen other than his own (he was talking about my overpronation). The picture of the insoles below should give an idea of how bad.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Insoles-003.jpg" alt="Custom insoles compare to regular insoles" />
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Insoles-006.jpg" alt="Custom insole compare to regular insoles" /></p>

<p>The custom insoles regularly cause blisters due to the slippy heat reflecting surface used to make them. In recent months I've started walking differently, no longer heal striking and have not used insoles for the last few months. So far I've had no knee pain, minimalist shoes have allowed me to get back to our natural way of walking and running.</p>

<p>Maybe eventually I can run barefoot but this will require some foot strengthening, the <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Keen_Mens_A86_TR_Trail_Runners_102848.html">A86s</a> and <a href="http://www.purekit.com/merrell-true-glove-barefoot-shoe-prod31665/">True Gloves</a> are helping to make this transition. Not that I have plans to go backpacking barefoot.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Icebreaker Mega Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/03/23/icebreaker-mega-review/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-23T21:03:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/03/23/icebreaker-mega-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Icebreaker-004.jpg" alt="Icebreaker Products" /></p>

<p>I was sorting through my walking gear and realised that certain manufacturers dominate my gear and the main reason for this is the quality of the their products. One of the dominant names is Icebreaker. Whenever I'm after base layers they are my goto brand, I've tried others but always return. Rather than writing a post on each item, I thought I'd write about them all in this one post. All the items I have bought, except for the Leggings (Long Johns) which were provided to me by Webtogs. All Icebreaker products below are 100% Merino wool from New Zealand. Many of the products come with a label that allows you to track the sheep the wool came from, I've never looked and just see it as a gimmick. The clothing is rated according to the weight of the merino wool used. **</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Icebreaker-011.jpg" alt="Mondo Zip" />**</p>

<p><strong>Mondo Zip (Bodyfit 200)</strong>
Price: £48
Weight: 238g (old one 241g)
Link: <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Icebreaker_Mens_Mondo_Zip_100087.html">Webtogs</a></p>

<p>This was the first Icebreaker bit of clothing I bought about 5 years ago, the grey top in the picture is the original top. It has been worn on countless trips and has outlasted a couple of other tops I've had from Smartwool and Alpkit. It is looking a bit faded but I still wear it regularly. The Mondo is a Skin 200 top which is in the Lite range. The black top next to the original grey is the same model but is only a year old, the fit has changed and it is now figure hugging (either that or I stretched the original). Luckily I am slim but if you weren't you maybe need to go up a size. The Mondo is the perfect base layer for 3 season use, I wear only this top and a light-speed in all but Winter and I'm always warm or cool enough. It features a zip neck collar which is my preference over T-shirt style.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Icebreaker-014-150x150.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>There's not a lot I can say, it feels comfortable, smart enough for the pub, warm even when damp and the essential for me: It doesn't stink even after several days of sweating in it, unlike most other tops I've tried. The only negative is the newer models have an inside label that is cracking compared to the old sewn fabric label, its not itchy but doesn't look good (see picture).</p>

<p><strong><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/2011-03-23-Icebreaker.jpg" alt="Tech Top" /></strong></p>

<p><strong>Tech Top (Bodyfit 260)</strong>
Price: £59.95
Weight: 377g
Link: <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Icebreaker_Mens_Tech_Top_100088-4135.html">Webtogs</a></p>

<p>This is my favourite top, I bought it before doing the West Highland Way in Winter because I wanted something a bit warmer. I wasn't disappointed, while the other top feels comfortable this you never want to take off. I've considered buying a few of these to wear at work, they would look smart enough but probably too warm. Like the Mondo this has a zip neck collar to keep you warm, it folds to look like a shirt collar. It's got a drop-tail to stop the base of your back from getting cold. The product description like the Mondo says "Fits close to the body" but I find it more a relaxed fit than the Mondo. There's also thumb loops that I know many find essential, strangely these aren't listed on Icebreakers site. **</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Icebreaker-008.jpg" alt="Leggings" />**</p>

<p><strong>Leggings w/Fly (Bodyfit 200)</strong>
Price: £43.29
Weight: 198g
Link: <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Icebreaker_Mens_Leggings_Light_Weight_100249.html">Webtogs</a></p>

<p>I have had some cheap Snow &amp; Rock Long Johns for a couple of years which I use when its cold to sleep in and wear snowboarding. I got these to replace them, they're just as warm but a lot lighter and made of Merino like the rest of my Icebreaker stuff. I have the 200 model which kept me warm under my Montane Terras while walking up Ben Nevis a few weeks ago. The fit is tight, my thighs are quite muscular but not huge. They are maybe a bit too tight when walking steep inclines or scrambling and could make it slightly harder work. Sizing up would be a good idea. For sleeping in I've found them luxurious, using them last weekend when the temperature dipped just below freezing they kept me toasty in my 0c sleeping bag. The merino feels soft and cosy against the skin and the fly comes in handy for those night trips out of the shelter. I'm not quite sure what the phrase "no compromise on sex appeal" means? The summary would be they keep you warm and feel excellent against the skin.
<strong>
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Icebreaker-007.jpg" alt="Boxers" /></strong></p>

<p><strong>Relaxed Boxer with Fly (Bodyfit 150)</strong>
Price: £24
Weight: 87g
Link: <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Icebreaker_Boxer_Brief_150_100089.html">Webtogs</a></p>

<p>For some reason I've not read many reviews of underwear, but its an item of clothing that could cause the most discomfort. Personally I prefer a boxer that is quite loose, especially when walking multiple days. Merino in my opinion is essential if wearing for more than a day. I wore a pair of these on the 2010 TGO challenge and carried a spare pair, after 9 days I changed to the spare only because I was carrying them. The pair I had been wearing still smelled as fresh as the day I put them on (which was clean). Maybe I should wear these as my day to day boxers, which could cut down on washing!! As the name implies the fit is loose without looking like a pair of bloomers. I own a few pairs of these and currently wouldn't buy anything else. **</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/2011-03-23-Icebreaker1.jpg" alt="Icebreaker Socks" />**</p>

<p><strong>Hiker Mid Crew Socks</strong>
Price: £10.50
Weight: 80g pair (Lite Hike: 74g)
Link: <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Icebreaker_Mens_Hiker_Mid_Crew_Socks_101603-13664.html">Webtogs</a></p>

<p>I've tried dozens of socks over the years and have generally struggled to find a pair that fit without them being too big or small. I am a size 8.5 and I find that with most brands the socks for my feet are just a bit too big and there is excess material, the sizing on these are perfect for me. Like with all the other Icebreaker products here these are Merino wool which I again for smell reasons I think are essential for multi-days. Merino also keeps my feet warm when wet, this is a big consideration when wearing trail runners. The socks are technical and by this I'm referring to re-inforced areas for your heal and toe, achilles protections and instep support. All this makes them feel very comfortable on your feet. I don't feel that I need these off my feet at the end of a walk, which I have had with other brands. These have been my socks of choice for the last 2 years, the only other socks I choose to wear are X-socks for running, but they pong after 1 run. I also have some <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Icebreaker_Mens_Hiker_Lite_Socks_100265.html">Icebreaker Hiker Lite </a>socks which are supposedly slightly more breathable but I'm hard pushed to tell the difference. **</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Buchaille-Etive-Mor-102.jpg" alt="Pocket 200 Hat" />**</p>

<p><strong>Pocket 200 Hat</strong>
Price: £16
Weight: 45g
Link: <a href="http://www.icebreaker.com/site/icebreaker_man_hats_200_pocket_200.html">Icebreaker</a></p>

<p>I started wearing this hat over a year ago and it's now the only hat I use. It is so small its easy to stow in a hip belt pocket along with other gear and forget it's there until you need it. I haven't got the best shaped head for hats, but on a normal person it would look fashionable and is also reversible. It's hard to believe that this thin merino hat would keep you warm, but its the only hat I've worn right through the winter without any problems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Montane Lite-Speed H2O Jacket Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/03/05/montane-lite-speed-h2o-jacket-review/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-05T16:28:54+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/03/05/montane-lite-speed-h2o-jacket-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Wolsingham-via-Thornley-010.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
<strong>Weight: </strong>170g (Medium)<br/>
<strong>Price:</strong> £67.49 (PureKit)<br/>
<strong>Product Page:</strong> <a href="http://www.purekit.com/montane-lite-speed-h20-jacket-prod81166/">PureKit</a></p>

<p><strong>Overview </strong> An ultra-lightweight minimalist waterproof jacket, claimed to be the worlds lightest hooded waterproof jacket that is intended for people moving fast and light in the mountains with its roots in mountain running.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>Features</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Roll-away hood</li>
<li>DWR coating</li>
<li>Taped seams</li>
<li>Carry bag</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/H2O-020.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
The whole point of this jacket is the lack of features which make it incredibly lightweight. There are no pockets or fancy wired hoods just taped seams, a basic roll-away hood and a DWR coating. I believe this is all you need from a Waterproof jacket which is only worn when its tipping it down with rain. Although I had no problems wearing it all day on my last trip when not raining.</p>

<p><strong>Detail</strong><br/>
I will say from the start I'm a huge fan of Montane products not because they are from the North East of England (my home), but because every peice of kit I've had from them has done the job asked of it. I've looked at the H2O for months, possibly because the burnt orange version can be seen from the international space station and you can't miss it in the shop. Personally I prefer to be a bit more stealthy and opted for the black. I would imagine most people are familiar with the standard Lite-speed its a windproof that to my mind is hard to beat. I'm currently on my second, but still use the original after 5 years. Every walk one comes with me, I can't think of another bit of kit I could say the same about. So putting Lite-speed in front of H2O set the bar high for me.</p>

<p>One thing to note on the tag attached to the H2O jacket it reads "moderately waterproof fabric" this is part of the reason I've been unsure about it, everywhere else the "moderately" is dropped. When you feel the Freeflow fabric it is hard to believe it could ever keep you dry and most Lite-speed users will of experienced wetting out if worn in the rain. The H2O uses different fabric, you could read more about it on the <a href="http://www.montane.co.uk/">Montane</a> site if so inclined, its lighter than Pertex but has a DWR coating.<br/>
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Adopted-Paths-Feb-2011-and-H2O-011.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
The first trip with the H2O was perfect testing weather, windy and chucking it down. This isn't a trip report so the summary; even in horizontal rain the jacket kept me dry with water beading and running off, to be certain I was totally dry I wore a light grey base layer underneath and there were no signs of damp patches. To say I was surprised would be an understatement, my dad who I walked with was also looking admiringly at it while he wore his <a href="http://www.montane.co.uk/products/men/shell/super-fly-jacket/419">Montane Super-fly</a> which is twice the weight and with more restricted movement.</p>

<p>I have used the jacket on several other trips, twice it sat in my bag while in Scotland not noticing it was there due to it minuscule size and weight. The last trip I walked 14 miles in the dry and used it instead of the Lite-speed, wearing it over the top of my base layer. This time I was expecting to get damp from the inside, which would of happened if I'd done this with my Quickfire jacket, once again to my surprise I remained dry, no sweating. It's hard to test without swapping jackets during a walk but I think the H2O is very slightly warmer probably due to the DWR coating, hence less breathable? I haven't been able to prove this yet.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/H2O-006.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
The hood was used on the 1st trip and kept my head/hat dry underneath, it appears to be slightly more shaped than the normal lite-speed hood but maybe that is just the taped seams. There is no wired hood but you don't need one, the hood isn't big enough to get in the way and simple one handed draw cords keep it tight. A baseball style cap can be used if needed.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/2011-03-05-H2O1.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
The jacket has reflective trim, which is basically reflective fabric used as a storm flap over the zip and is also sown in various other places to allow you to be seen at night. I prefer this to reflective stickers/patches used on the regular Lite-speed which are pealing off the newest one, making it look old before its time. Interestingly the old style stickers on the 5 year old model are still OK.</p>

<p>As noted at the top of this article the H2O weighs 170g and the stuff sack 13g yet strangely my scale shows 182g when in the stuff sack. This must be due to the way the scale rounds off. Compare this to the regular non-waterproof which is 1g heavier. You may wonder why the waterproof is lighter, this is due to no pocket, a slimmer fit and slightly lighter fabric. The slimmer fit is quite noticeable, I almost ordered a small but pleased I didn't.</p>

<p>The last thing to note is the stuff sack has a velcro strap which allows you to fix it to somewhere in/on your pack. The regular has a carabiner style clip which can be a pain with very cold hands, no such problems with the velcro fastener.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/2011-03-05-H2O.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
One minor gripe and this is for all of the newer light Montane jackets why did they change the zip pull from my 5 year old Lite-speed. It had a long piece of fabric used for the pull which was easily found, the short plastic ones on all newer models are a nightmare to get hold of. The image above doesn't show the H2O but the zip is the same as the New Lite-Speed pull.</p>

<p>Montane has updated the jacket while I have been testing this one, the colours are now Shadow grey / tangerine (zips), Electric blue / tangerine (zips), Fluoro yellow (<a href="http://www.montane.co.uk/products/men/shell/lite-speed-h2o-jacket/164">see here</a>). It is sad to see the black dropped, although most shops will still have the old colours for a while yet and the price shown above reflects this. The only other change I can see is the 360 reflective sticker things they've added which is a negative, rather than the sown reflective fabric on my test one. The 360 ones are the same as the ones pealing off my regular Lite-speed.</p>

<p><strong>Pros:</strong> lightweight, packability, price<br/>
<strong>Cons:</strong> durability, lack of pockets?</p>

<p><strong>Summary </strong><br/>
The H2O is a pleasant surprise, the weight and packability are a huge draw. Surprisingly keeping me dry during a deluge. I have slight concerns over how effective the DWR coating will be after extended use, but so far its keeping me dryer than my regular Event jacket. For the price I think it is perfect for 3 season day walk use, where you keep it in your pack in case of a downpour. Personally I am happy using it on multi-day trips but would be unsure for long trips without extended testing. My only wish is that it was available as a smock, which would be even lighter. At the current reduced price of the model I have can you not buy it?</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong> I was sent this by <a href="http://www.purekit.com/">Purekit</a> to review, as with anything I review I will always write exactly what I think, even if it is a negative review.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
