<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[StevenHorner.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-29T13:25:58+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Horner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The John Muir Trail]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2015/05/29/the-john-muir-trail/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-29T13:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2015/05/29/the-john-muir-trail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4086/5087637429_425bf158d0_z.jpg" title="John Muir Trail by advencap" alt="John Muir Trail by advencap" /></p>

<p>Once again the blog has been silent for a while, so many things have been going on recently. The biggest single thing is organising my wedding to Traci or rather our Honeymoon walking the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Muir_Trail">John Muir Trail</a>. The wedding itself is very simple with just Traci, myself and the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/LasVegasWeddingWagon">wedding wagon</a> marrying us on the balcony of our <a href="http://www.cosmopolitanlasvegas.com/">Cosmopolitan</a> suite in Las Vegas.</p>

<p><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/7/6225/6334704799_f67dbe38c5_b.jpg" title="Panorama by Henry Egghart" alt="Panorama by Henry Egghart" /></p>

<h3>So what&#8217;s this John Muir Trail then?</h3>

<p>For me personally the John Muir Trail came to my attention about 5 years ago from conversations with <a href="https://twitter.com/MrPhilTurner">Phil Turner</a>, I subsequently bought the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1852843969/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1852843969&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkId=YM2LA5B3G464XUZI">Cicerone Guide</a> glanced at it then it sat on my shelf unread. I have spent quite a bit of time on and off over the intervening years looking at pictures and stories of those that have walked it. So what is it&#8230;</p>

<p>It&#8217;s a 211 mile walk in the Sierra Nevada mountain range in California, which passes through several national parks (Yosemite, King&#8217;s Canyon, John Muir and Ansel Adams wildernesses and Sequoia). Usually starting in Yosemite Valley and ending on the summit of Mt Whitney, which is the highest mountain in the contiguous United States (the 48 adjoining states) at 14,505 ft (4,421 m). Nearly all of the route lies over 8,000 ft in elevation and a third at over 10,000 ft. To put this in perspective, the highest mountain in the UK is Ben Nevis at a mere 4,409 ft.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mt_Height.jpg" title="Mountain Heights" alt="Mountain Heights" /></p>

<p>We couldn&#8217;t acquire permits for the regular south bound route described above, the idea of permits is a strange concept to us UK walkers. In the US it&#8217;s more common and helps to keep popular routes wild by limiting the numbers of people allowed to walk the trail.  I will go into more detail regarding permits in another post, but we managed to secure a permit in the opposite direction (North Bound). The John Muir Trail may end or start in our case on Mt Whitney but unless we could parachute in we need to walk to the summit.  The closest starting point (Trail head) is Whitney portal but this is one of the most popular starting points in the US due to Mt Whitneys height. We have to start from a Trail head further South at Horseshoe Meadows, this will add an extra 22 miles to our route.</p>

<p><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/3/2322/2452478950_6cd7e03f22_z.jpg" title="Half Dome, Liberty Cap and Nevada Falls in Yosemite by Miguel Vieira" alt="Half Dome, Liberty Cap and Nevada Falls in Yosemite by Miguel Vieira" /></p>

<h3>How long will it take?</h3>

<p>Many people take 3 weeks, but after looking at lots of trip reports most of these appear to be a lot slower than we travel or carry huge packs, stop to fish, video the route, etc. So after what feels like months I have a schedule which I think looks realistic. We are aiming to complete the walk in 14 days, we may extend this by a couple of days as there are a couple of long 20+ mile days but these are when our packs are at their lightest and well into the walk. We intend to take it easy at the start to acclimatise to the altitude and the packs will be heavy with 10 days of food. I&#8217;m not going to post the actual schedule, it will very likely change as we are walking.</p>

<p><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/4/3155/3026838050_c40d39cdc3_z.jpg" title="Palisade Creek Canyon by sheenjek" alt="Palisade Creek Canyon by sheenjek" /></p>

<h3>Planning</h3>

<p>Planning any walk can feel like a military operation and can be stressful, but when it&#8217;s abroad for any extended period and you have the added event of a wedding it becomes a lot of work. I&#8217;m sure the planning is simple compared to long distance walks like the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Crest_Trail">PCT</a> or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continental_Divide_Trail">CDT</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Permits</li>
<li>Food</li>
<li>Transport</li>
<li>Accommodation</li>
<li>Storage (wedding items)</li>
<li>Insurance?</li>
</ul>


<p>These have been the biggest headaches, but gradually I hope I have solved all of them. I hope to write some future posts covering some of these before we actually set off and update them once we return but I can&#8217;t commit 100% to that.</p>

<p>All pictures in this post are copyright <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">Creative Commons</a> to their respected attributed owners.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/14657061@N00/5087637429">John Muir Trail by advencap</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/65738506@N08/6334704799">Panorama by Henry Egghart</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/miguelvieira/2452478950">Half Dome, Liberty Cap and Nevada Falls in Yosemite by Miguel Vieira</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sheenjek/3026838050">Palisade Creek Canyon by sheenjek</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kitty's Wood PRoW Success]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2015/01/19/kittys-wood-prow-success/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-19T17:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2015/01/19/kittys-wood-prow-success</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/PROW/FootpathMap.jpg" alt="PRoW Signs" /></p>

<p>This website has been on hold for a while, unfortunately I didn&#8217;t do a lot of walking in 2014. A few walks locally, the Durham Dales Challenge, Scarborough to Whitby, a couple of walks in the lakes and a trip or two to Scotland. In previous years I would have done this in 1 month.</p>

<p>Traci and I have a few things planned for 2015, the biggest of which will be our July wedding in Las Vegas. Our Honeymoon will be walking the John Muir Trail (presuming we get permits) then returning to Las Vegas to relax, if that&#8217;s possible in Vegas.</p>

<p>The main reason for this post is to provide an update on the footpaths around the area I live and in particular Kitty&#8217;s Wood. I wrote about the situation back in June 2012. A quick refresh to save reading the full post is the local land was previously owned by Durham County Council and leased as a farm. The farm closed several years ago and was demolished in April 2009, the Council then decided to sell off the land. The farm land had lots of footpaths across it that locals had walked for years and the Council had maintained, but the council had never added these paths as official Public Rights of Way (PRoW). The new land owner then decided to close the majority of these paths which angered a lot of people.</p>

<p>My take on this was always that the main problem was with the Council in the first place. Selling the land without making these paths PRoW, the land owner legally was perfectly in his rights to stop people walking across them. Even though he must surely have known the extent to which these paths were used, but probably didn&#8217;t expect the response. In any case this led to considerable effort by a small group of locals and later the <a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/">Ramblers</a> to have these paths officially recognised.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/PROW/Sign_stile_wire.jpg" alt="Stile" /></p>

<p>I am happy to report that almost all of the footpaths I originally highlighted are now official PRoW, with a couple of exceptions. Seven new paths have been added to the definitive map and in due course will appear on Ordnance Survey maps. I have already updated <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=16/54.7235/-1.7650&amp;layers=C">OpenStreetMap</a> with these paths and their official designations.</p>

<p>I would encourage everyone to check their local footpaths to ensure they are recorded as official PRoW. If you find they are not, then you need to collect evidence of their use with written statements from as many people as possible but these will likely need to be recorded on the correct forms and a modification order will need to be applied for all this should be explained by your local council. My experience of the process was not good, requests to apply for a modification order were ignored or people were told the <a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/">Ramblers</a> had already applied but this turned out to not include the same information or the same paths.</p>

<p>The whole process is not easy for an individual to carry out unless you have experience of the process or have lots of spare time, most of us don&#8217;t. I would encourage you to approach the Ramblers who do have plenty of experience of this sort of thing and my local Council took more notice of them than anyone else.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/PROW/Signpost.jpg" alt="Signpost" /></p>

<p>There are still a couple of paths missing or recorded incorrectly, a footpath that was always used as a bridleway and did have a bridleway sign at each end up until a few years ago is still only recorded as a footpath (FP 43/45). A short footpath which even has a Durham County Council sign on it has not been added as a PROW and several footpaths which are still marked incorrectly (FP 45). Again these are failings from the PRoW team at the Council who would only listen to the <a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/">Ramblers</a> and told others that they had applied for all the same footpaths, which is why these are missing. The existing footpaths which are marked incorrectly I have reported to them repeatedly long before the land was sold and nothing has ever been done. The whole thing highlights just how difficult it can be for individuals.</p>

<p>I would really like to see the <a href="http://www.thebmc.co.uk/">British Mountaineering Council (BMC)</a> help in this area, they appear to be increasing their support for walkers in recognition that the majority of their members are more likely walkers not Alpine mountaineers. They are moving in the right direction with the help of people like <a href="https://www.thebmc.co.uk/chris-townsend-becomes-the-bmcs-first-hill-walking-ambassador">Chris Townsend</a> and <a href="https://www.thebmc.co.uk/BMC-appoints-first-ever-hill-walking-officer">Carey Davis</a> but appreciate they focus on Mountain areas.</p>

<p>The problems faced by the public appear to be stacking up, there are deadlines for claiming footpaths but Councils and the <a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/">Ramblers</a> appear to be working to differing information. With an increasing backlog of work for PRoW teams and dwindling staff numbers, resources and uncertainty for those that remain I can feel for them, I&#8217;m in the same situation myself.</p>

<p>The public need help and guidance from the likes of the Ramblers and the <a href="http://www.thebmc.co.uk/">BMC</a> preferably a combined message. We are all working for the same thing after all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Walking Mt Toubkal]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2014/04/25/walking-mt-toubkal/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-25T16:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2014/04/25/walking-mt-toubkal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20094.JPG" alt="Aroumd" /></p>

<p>Myself and Traci actually did this walk 18 months ago in June 2013, but for some reason I never got around to writing it up. I made extensive notes on the actual days and this is the write up of those notes. Hopefully someone will find this useful.</p>

<p>We were looking for a summer holiday to relax but me being me, I wanted something a bit different. I have always hated sitting around a pool or lazing on a beach. Initially we were looking at Greece and I was contemplating adding a walk up Mount Olympus as you do on your relaxing summer holiday. Yet even with the supposed problems with the Greek economy at the time the holidays were still expensive. I decided to see what else was available that had mountains nearby. Somewhere I had never considered jumped out at me when I realised that the Atlas mountains were close by. The destination was Marrakech.</p>

<p>The obvious target if you have a couple of days to walk in the Atlas mountain is Mt Toubkal, the highest mountain in North Africa at 13,671 ft (4,167 m). It&#8217;s a big step up in height for anyone used to the mountains of the UK and something else to consider is the heat in summer.</p>

<h2>Planning</h2>

<p>I started planning the walk several months before the trip and found a couple of useful sites on the internet, the best of which is <a href="http://www.brainstorming.co.uk/walking/mounttoubkalroutedescription.html">here</a> where you can also download KML files of the route. You will also need a map and the best map available from my research is the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1904207472/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1904207472&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21">Cordee Toubkal and Marrakech Map at 1:50,000</a>. Most of the other maps are less detailed or old.</p>

<p>I also bought the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1873756771/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1873756771&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21">Moroccan Atlas - The Trekking Guide Book</a> which has a detailed drawn map of the route with lots of extra information.</p>

<h2>Huts or Camping</h2>

<p>The previously mentioned site describes doing it in 1 day, which is certainly achievable if you can set off early, know you are fine at altitude and are fit. My plan was to take 2 days and stay in a one of the refuges on the mountain. There are 2 to choose from and are next door to each other at the South col. The original French <a href="http://www.refugedutoubkal.com/en/index.html">CAF Neltner</a> hut or the newer <a href="http://www.refugetoubkal.com/uk/">Les Mouflon de Toubkal</a> which is where I chose.</p>

<p>I contacted Les Mouflon de Toubkal by email a couple of months before our trip and booked 2 beds in the dormitory which we were told would cost 286 MAD (£21) each for dinner, bed and breakfast. I beleive this is now 319 MAD (£23.50) each. When we actually got there I was told the dorm would be 500 MAD (£37) for us as a couple, so a little cheaper. We decided to actually pay the extra for a room, which cost us 800 MAD (£59) and personally I think this is a better option. The cost of a room is now 950 MAD (£70).</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20032.JPG" alt="camping" />
The camping options are limited at higher altitudes, due to the ground being very rocky. You can pay at the refuge for a dusty pitch for 20 MAD (£1.50), there were a few tents slightly below the refuge but I&#8217;m not sure I would want to be pitched there.</p>

<h2>Food and Water</h2>

<p>You need to plan your food and water carefully, the temperatures can be over 40c in Imlil and once out of the village there is no shade. We carried around 4-5 litres of water for the trip from Imlil to the hostel. To be honest this was not enough between 2 of us in the temperatures we experiences at the height of the day.</p>

<p>There are places on the way up where you can buy water or other drinks. Yet most were closed when we passed, other than at Sidi Chamharouch where there were several places you could sit down and drink or hide from the sun. We didn&#8217;t stop here though due to time. As for food, again the same places that sold drinks also would have a few things, generally fruit. This was probably our weakest point, the only food we took with us we had scavenged from our hotel breakfast, mainly bread. Plan this better than we did, you will need fuel.</p>

<p>Once you reach the refuge you can buy an array of food from sweets like Snickers and Mars bars to full meals. You can also buy bottled water but it is expensive because it has to be carried up by mule.</p>

<h2>Getting there</h2>

<p>The easiest way to get to Imlil from Marrakech is to take a Grand Taxi from the Taxi rank which can be found to the South West of the medina, outside Bab er Rob. The taxi rank is quite large but is further outside the medina than I had expected along a dusty road. Although more buildings have been built in the area now.</p>

<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d13591.061720552316!2d-7.992708643123295!3d31.612886692871932!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x33f214a09ef67a41!2sStation+De+Taxis+Charij+Lbguer!5e0!3m2!1sen!2suk!4v1398419080540" width="600" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:0"></iframe>


<p>On our way to the to the Taxi rank a minibus pulled up and we were asked if we were heading to Imlil, we agreed to pay 22 MAD (£1.60) each. An absolute bargain, but the minibus was a 12 seater and there were around 20 of us in it. When we arrived at Asni it got very confusing, we were ushered out of the minibus but we had no idea where we should be going. Luckily 3 teenagers who had been in the minibus directed us to a grand taxi. I shared the front passenger seat with Traci, the teenagers shared the back seat with another local couple. The smell of petrol was overpowering, even with all of the windows open. The journey from Asni to Imlil felt precarious along a roughish road, swerving around people selling fruit and trucks seemingly abandoned in the middle of road while they talked to people on the roadside. We were deposited at a taxi rank which is on the left side as you arrive in Imlil (open triangular area to the right of the road on the embedded map).</p>

<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m13!1m11!1m3!1d1005.790170907319!2d-7.920615930159965!3d31.137186968049317!2m2!1f0!2f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!5e1!3m2!1sen!2suk!4v1398420469471" width="600" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:0"></iframe>


<p> If you planned to walk the route in a day you would need to stay in Imlil, unless you managed to arrive a lot earlier than we did. There were various places advertising rooms as we walked up the bank from the taxi rank. A search on Google will find several for around 200 MAD (£15) B&amp;B.</p>

<h2>The Walk</h2>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/DSCF1829.JPG" alt="Aroumd" />
We set off from Imlil after being dropped off at around 11:30. The village was very busy with vehicles, mules and people rushing around. I always find the hardest part of a walk navigationally is the start when leaving an unknown town or village.</p>

<p>I am always raring to set off and should take time to orientate yourself and map, I had taken the time at home to scan and geo-reference my paper map. so I now had a digital map on my phone which helped locate myself in Imlil and confirm I was indeed heading the direction I thought I was.</p>

<p>We found the track out of the village quite easily but found we had crossed the stream too early and were heading up to Aroumd (marked Around on the Cordee map) earlier than intended. This involved a steep climb through the trees but I could see we would join on to the same path. We walked through the edge of the village, passing a small group of children laughing and playing. As we walked by a small girl spat at me, I didn&#8217;t actually notice as she she was behind me. It appeared almost as if she had been dared to do it.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20092.JPG" alt="Flood plain" />
After leaving Aroumd behind there is a large rocky open area which looks like a flood plain but was bone dry when we walked. After the the flat stony expanse, you start the climb on a very obvious path. From here on the route is very easy to follow and you rarely need to consult the map, other than checking points off as you climb higher.</p>

<p>I would recommend the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1873756771/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1873756771&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21">Moroccan Atlas Book</a> purely for the hand drawn maps. The Cordee map does not have the detail to help with the navigation out of Imlil, its the hand drawn maps that allowed me to see my route up to Aroumd would join onto the same track I had intended to take. After the climb from the flood plain, I never used the hand drawn maps again until I returned to the same point the next day.</p>

<p>The walking is quite easy, although a constant climb it&#8217;s on a track the mules travel daily up to the refuge. Your energy is sapped by the heat and once out of the trees near Imlil there is no escape from the sun. The temperature was in the high 30&#8217;s celsius with no let up all day.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20089.JPG" alt="Sidi Chamharouch" />
I don&#8217;t intend to write a detailed description of the walk up to the refuge, it&#8217;s too long ago and there are various books and websites which do a better job than I could. As we walked higher we did pass a few places that would be selling drinks and fruit, but they were closed maybe because it was now the middle of the day. They are just stalls or tiny stone buildings at the side of the track.</p>

<p>Some of these places are marked on the hand drawn maps in the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1873756771/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1873756771&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21">Moroccon Atlas book</a>. The last place you could actually find a proper place to buy drinks or take a rest is at Sidi Chamharouch, there were 2 places I spotted selling drinks and a few small places selling scarves and other items. The hamlet is built around a muslim shrine. You can see a large whitewashed rock as you pass. You cross over a bridge and again climb steeply. I can remember thinking the section above the hamlet must be the hardest part for the mules.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/DSCF1842.JPG" alt="Mules" />
Mules are the only way items can be brought to places above the flood plain we passed earlier, their destinations would be the 2 refuge higher up or Sidi Chamharouch. It&#8217;s amazing watching the array of items the mules are carrying from gas bottles to building supplies and of course food. We felt sorry for the mules often struggling up or down steep sections overburdened with supplies. Our walk up was surprisingly quiet, the higher we got the more people we saw heading in the opposite direction. Some of the mules were carrying people who were too lazy to walk or their luggage.  We also passed several groups who were being lead by guides.</p>

<p>There are lots of mention of guides when researching the walk up to Mt. Toubkal, I chose not to pay for one. There was honestly no need, the route is very easy to follow. In winter my advice would likely be different, unless you had plenty of experience. You will be bombarded with people back in Imlil asking if you want a guide. Clearly this is a source of employment for people in the area but in summer an experienced walker would not need one. If you do decide to pay for a guide be careful to get one who can clearly speak your language, many spoke French better than English.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20024.JPG" alt="Traci and the path" />
We made good progress keeping a slow but steady pace, we were beginning to wonder if we were ever going to reach the refuge. The water was running low and the blazing sun which was being shaded slightly by cloud now was still very strong. We were starting to feel more tired than expected, probably due to the heat and the altitude. As our energy started to sap the refuge came into view. We stopped to eat some of the bread we had taken from breakfast and drink some of our remaining water. Looking up there were still odd patches of snow in places clinging on in shaded areas above us. There were a few tents below the buildings, I was happy we hadn&#8217;t decided to camp up here.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20081.JPG" alt="Refuge" />
We were booked into the Les Mouflon de Toubkal, walking through the door at 16:30 we couldn&#8217;t see a thing until our eyes adjusted to the darkness.</p>

<p>There were a small number of people inside, some clearly who worked there. Most did not speak English and wore traditional clothes. This was in contrast to the person who appeared to be running the refuge who spoke perfect English and wore clothes like we would wear back home, T-shirt and jeans if I recall correctly.</p>

<p>We had booked 2 beds in a dorm but decided once we got there to change to a private room. We were pleased we did, there was a large number of older Japanese hikers staying who were very loud. We just wanted to relax and this would have been hard with the noise from the group. We were given some mint tea, which is very refreshing and is drank everywhere we went in Morocco.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20039.JPG" alt="Room in the refuge" />
<img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20037.JPG" alt="view from room" />
The room we were given was just off the open area and had a view back down the valley we had walked up. There were 2 single beds in the room with thick blankets. We had considered bringing sleeping bags, but instead brought just sleeping bag liners to protect us from any bed bugs, etc. I think this was a good idea, the blankets felt very itchy but cosy and warm.  We asked for an evening meal, I can&#8217;t remember if we had any choice but it was the best meal either of us had ever had. We think it was lamb tagine, but its possible it was goat. No matter what meat it was, Traci still states it was the best meal she has ever eaten. We had a large Tagine and bread to ourselves and would highly recommend doing this rather than carrying your own food up.</p>

<p>We arranged to have some breakfast ready for 6:30 the following day, then headed to bed to read and relax before going to sleep.</p>

<p>We had a very broken nights sleep due to strange loud noises all through the night, which sounded like tunneling beneath the refuge. This was the only negative thing about our stay there. They even had flushing toilets, unless I imagined that. We got up at 6:15 and our breakfast was already out for us with hot water for coffee brought once we sat at the table. Breakfast was jam and bread, we took some of the bread to eat during the day. We also bought 2 bottles of water and snickers before we left at 7:10.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20079.JPG" alt="view back to refuge" />
The path above the refuge crosses in front of a waterfall and steeply up a scree slope. We missed the track to the left which avoids the worst of the scree. Traci was struggling and was having problems with earache caused by the strong winds and possibly the altitude. She was also struggling to catch her breath and started telling me to do it on my own. We either did it together or we went down together.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20046.JPG" alt="boulders" />
We carried on and found a path marked by cairns. The wind was lighter in the gully and the sun hadn&#8217;t reached us yet due to the mountainsides. It was slow going, finding ourselves out of breath sooner than as UK heights. Traci was feeling it more than me, but I was happy to stop and catch my own breath. We worked our way up, we could see 2 hikers in the distance with the gap to them steadily decreasing. The path split into three at some point and we missed the initial split but stuck to the right where the scree was easier to cross.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20057.JPG" alt="Top of gully" />
A man travelling fast up towards us, soon caught us up. I&#8217;m not sure of his nationality, he may have been Moroccan but he spoke good English. Explaining it was his second time up having to return for pictures after his camera had been either lost or stolen. Soon after this we reached the top of the gully and the ridge where we turned left, continuing to follow the clear path. We passed the 2 hikers we had been closing in on, two women.</p>

<p>Shortly after passing the women we passed another 2 groups who were heading down. The first who were French, spoke to us in English telling us it was about 40 minutes to the top. Traci thought they were joking, thinking we were almost there. The group of 3 was British with a guide. The young lady looked ina bad way, clearly struggling and in tears. The guide was helping her down as best he could.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20061.JPG" alt="summit in view" />
A couple of minutes after this the summit came into view but the track went to the left of the ridge before heading to the right and the summit. It took around 20 minutes.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20073.JPG" alt="Summit of Mt Toubkal" />
<img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/DSCF1871.JPG" alt="us on the summit" />
We met the guy at the top who had lost his pictures on his previous trip. We took pictures for each other before he left us alone at the summit. After around 20 minutes we decided to head back down as we were leaving the two ladies we past earlier had arrived and asked us to take pictures for them.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/marrakech/Marrakech%20095.JPG" alt="Nearly back to Imlil" />
We descended fast retracing our path, which was more obvious on the descent. We didn&#8217;t hang around when we reached the refuge but continued on. We stopped to eat some of our bread below the refuge, it took less than 2 hours from the refuge to Sidi Chamharouch and the white rock which we passed quickly. There were a lot less people on our return journey.</p>

<p>Twenty minutes later and we were at the zigzags above the flood plain. I decided to ignore the route description and head the more obvious route which was far easier and faster.</p>

<p>We arrived in Imlil just before 4pm and bartered for a grand taxi back to Marrakech for 200 MAD (£15), although I also had to pay the guy I was bartering with not the driver. The smallest amount I had was 50 MAD (£3.66). We had the taxi to ourselves this time, although the driver was crazy, driving very fast, over taking vehicles with cars heading towards us. He had to go onto the dirt at the side of the road to avoid collisions on more than one occasion. We were pleased when we made it back to Bab er Rob and the Taxi rank in one piece.</p>

<p>I was conscious that we could make the last free shuttle bus of the day back to our hotel if we were fast. I set off at pace for the pickup point, but Traci was struggling to keep up. We made it to the shuttle bus with a minute to spare before it arrived.</p>

<p>We both loved the walk and Morocco, we returned the following year for a more relaxing holiday. I would highly recommend Marrakech and the walk up Mt. Toubkal.</p>

<p>You can find the zipped GPX track for the 2 days <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/files/Toubkal.zip">here</a>, which could help with timings and the actual route we took.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Most Visible Mountain &amp; New Mountain Classifications]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/11/09/the-most-visible-mountain-and-new-mountain-classifications/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-09T17:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/11/09/the-most-visible-mountain-and-new-mountain-classifications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/StobBinnein.png" alt="The Most Visible Mountain in Scotland" /></p>

<p>The most successful projects, to me at least, are those where you learn so much more than you ever expected to. I started the Peak Visibility project to find the answer to what seamed like a very simple question &#8220;Which Scottish Mountain can you see the most?&#8221;. You can find out how this question arose in the <a href="http://stevenhorner.com/blog/2013/08/30/the-most-visible-mountain-in-scotland/" title="First Peak Visiblity Post">first Peak Visibility post</a> or at the end of this post.</p>

<p>It was not quite as simple as I had thought, the first thing was to define the question more specifically.</p>

<p>I decided to limit my criteria to Munro (mountains in Scotland over 3000 feet), this reduced the list considerably down to 282 mountains at the current count. I then set the criteria, which I defined as &#8220;If I stood on the highest point of the mountain (summit) what land would be visible&#8221;, this would give me the answer &#8220;Which summits could I see from any point in Scotland&#8221;. I also decided I could also work out &#8220;If I stood on a Munro summit which other summits could I see&#8221;.</p>

<h2>The Top 10 most visible Munro in Scotland.</h2>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/PeakVisibilityTop10.png" alt="Top 10 Visible Scottish Munro" /></p>

<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1" style="width: 600px;">
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th scope="col">
                        No.</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Name</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Height (metres)</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Height (feet)</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        <p>
                            Visible Area (km2)</p>
                    </th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Visible Munro</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; white-space: pre-wrap; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">1</span></span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">Stob Binnein</span></span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1165</span></span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3822</span></span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">5454.05</span></span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">174</span></span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">2</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben More</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1174</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3852</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">5395.04</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">178</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">3</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Lawers</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1214</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3983</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">5284.86</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">205</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">4</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Macdui</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1309</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4295</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4570.33</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">216</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">5</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Lochnagar</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1155</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3789</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4178.17</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">147</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">6</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Cairn Gorm</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1244</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4081</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4038.33</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">180</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">7</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Cruachan</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1126</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3694</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3851.54</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">187</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">8</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Lui</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1130</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3707</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3782.59</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">143</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">9</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Braeriach</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1296</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4252</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3686.65</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">113</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">10</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Nevis</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1344</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4409</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3454.84</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">205</span></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>


<p>The table above may be different to many would have expected, yes Ben Nevis and Ben Macdui are in there. When you actually think about it they both have some very large neighbours which block the view. Both also have quite large summit plateaus. For a view on Ben Nevis I have always walked away from the summit, close to the edge. I am still waiting to see anything though after 7 cloudy summit visits.</p>

<p>The top 2 Stob Binnein and Ben More are next to each other and are often tackled in a <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/lochlomond/ben-more.shtml" title="Stob Binnein &amp; Ben More walk">single day walk</a>. There are not too many other high mountains within the immediate vicinity. If you ignore the few Munro to the South West, the next closest Munro is 5 miles away (Sgiath Chuil) and is quite low.</p>

<p>Compare that to Ben Macdui which has Braeriach and Cairn Gorm very close along with a host of other Munro in all directions, these block the viewability yet Ben Macdui still manages position number 4.</p>

<h2>The Least visible Munro in Scotland</h2>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/Bottom10.png" alt="The Bottom 10 Visible Munro" /></p>

<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1" style="width: 600px;">
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th scope="col">
                        No.</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Name</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Height (metres)</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Height (feet)</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        <p>
                            Visible Area (km2)</p>
                    </th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Visible Munro</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; white-space: pre-wrap; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">273</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Beinn Liath Mhor</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">926</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3038</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">162.63</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">33</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">274</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Beinn a&#39;Chaorainn</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1052</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3451</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">154.92</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">28</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">275</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ciste Dhubh</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">979</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3212</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">144.54</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">39</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">276</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">The Devil&#39;s Point</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1004</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3294</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">138.94</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">19</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">277</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Stob Poite Coire Ardair</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1054</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3458</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">136.16</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">15</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">278</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Sgurr na Carnach</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1002</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3287</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">126.99</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">34</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <font face="arial, sans, sans-serif" size="2">279</font></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">An Socach</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">921</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3022</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">114.43</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">27</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">280</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Sgurr na Sgine</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">946</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3104</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">102.14</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">43</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">281</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Meall Garbh</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">968</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3176</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">95.88</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">43</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">282</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; white-space: pre-wrap; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">Carn Aosda</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">917</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3009</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">30.21</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">9</span></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>


<p>The Visible Area column of the 2 tables above show the number of square Kilometres the summits can be viewed from (or be seen from). The higher the number the larger the area it can be seen from. Something to note, these figures are on land only. I masked the sea, but does includes visibility from land locked lochs.</p>

<h2>Highest number of visible Munro</h2>

<p>I mentioned that I could work out which other Munro you could see from the top of each Munro. Looking at the data this way gives a different list.</p>

<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1" style="width: 600px;">
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th scope="col">
                        No.</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Name</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Height (metres)</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Height (feet)</th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        <p>
                            Visible Area (km2)</p>
                    </th>
                    <th scope="col">
                        Visible Munro</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        1</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Macdui</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1309</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4295</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4570.33</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">216</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        2</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Geal-charn</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1132</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3714</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1903.89</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">213</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        3=</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Lawers</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1214</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3983</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">5284.86</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">205</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        3=</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Nevis</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1344</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4409</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3454.84</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">205</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        5</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Creag Meagaidh</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1128</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3701</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1986.23</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">198</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        6</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Stob Choire Claurigh</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1177</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3862</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">2114.97</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">193</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        7</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Ben Alder</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1148</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3766</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">2082.27</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">190</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        8=</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Cairn Toul</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1291</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">4236</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">2574.53</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">189</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        8=</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Aonach Beag</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1115.7</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3660</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1466.08</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">189</span></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        10</td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif;">Monadh Mor</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1113</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">3652</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">1710.43</span></td>
                    <td>
                        <span style="font-size: 13px; font-family: arial, sans, sans-serif; text-align: right;">188</span></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>


<p>There are a few similar names in the list, Ben Macdui, Ben Nevis and Ben Lawers but Geal-charn?</p>

<p>I will be honest that I had never heard of Geal-charn yet there are actually 4 Munros with the same name, 2 &#8220;Geal-charn&#8221; and 2 spelt &#8220;Geal charn&#8221; without the hyphen. The one in the table above is North West of Ben Alder at grid ref NN469746. This almost topped the list, until I re-ran the data in newer software it was relegated to Number 2.</p>

<h2>New Classifications</h2>

<p>For a bit of fun I decided that from the data I have produced I would create 2 new Classifications like Munro, Marilyns, Wainwrights etc. The new ones are Horners and Tracis.</p>

<h3>Mountains Classified as Horners</h3>

<div><script src="https://embed.github.com/view/geojson/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/master/Horners/Horners.geojson"></script></div>


<p>A mountain summit which can be viewed from 1000 square Kilometres excluding from the sea. There are currently 112 Horners and if you have completed the Munros then you have done them. This will change though and will expand to include all of Great Britain (Scotland, England and Wales).</p>

<p>Why create more classifications, becuase many of us like lists and these are slightly different to the thers which are normally based on height and/or drop.</p>

<p>You can download the list of Horners below, this list can easily be linked to The Database of British and Irish Hills by using the Number column (it is their number).</p>

<p>Download the Horners in the following formats: <a href="https://raw.github.com/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/master/Horners/Horners.csv" title="Horners CSV">CSV</a>, <a href="https://github.com/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/blob/master/Horners/Horners.zip?raw=true" title="Horners Shapefile">SHP</a>, <a href="https://raw.github.com/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/master/Horners/Horners.geojson" title="Horners geojson">GeoJSON</a>.</p>

<h3>Mountains Classified as Tracis</h3>

<div><script src="https://embed.github.com/view/geojson/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/master/Tracis/Tracis.geojson"></script></div>


<p>A 3000 foot mountain summit where you can view at least 100 other 3000 foot mountain summits. There are currently 75 Tracis all in Scotland. It doesn&#8217;t take a genius to work out that there will be none in England or Wales because there aren&#8217;t enough mountains over 3000 feet there to make the grade unless you can see enough of the Scottish Munro from the Skiddaw.</p>

<p>Why call these Tracis, they are named after my long suffering Girlfriend who has had to put up with me working for weeks/months on the Peak Visibility Project often late into the night while she is trying to sleep with me randomly talking to myself working out heights, distances, projections and various other related stuff. The Tracis are also something special just like her, oh and she will likely have to put up with me dragging her up all of them.</p>

<p>You can download the list of Tracis below, this list can easily be linked to The Database of British and Irish Hills by using the Number column (it is their number).</p>

<p>Download the Tracis in the following formats: <a href="https://raw.github.com/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/master/Tracis/Tracis.csv" title="Tracis CSV">CSV</a>, <a href="https://github.com/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/blob/master/Tracis/Tracis(shp).zip?raw=true" title="Tracis shapefile">SHP</a>, <a href="https://raw.github.com/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/master/Tracis/Tracis.geojson" title="Tracis geojson">GeoJSON</a>.</p>

<h2>Schiehallion?</h2>

<p>So what happened to Schiehallion?</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/schiehallion.png" alt="Schiehallion rank" /></p>

<p>Schiehallion is down there in position number 83 on Visibility. Something to be aware of is that the whole data is worked out on the visibility of the actual summit. If you have ever walked up Ben Nevis via the tourist route you will know you can&#8217;t see the summit until near the end of the walk. The summit is completely hidden by the mass of the mountain. So thinking about it a mountain that is pointy, quite high and not surrounded by too many high mountains should rank highly.</p>

<h2>Errors, thanks and stuff</h2>

<p>I will start by saying I am confident this data is not 100% accurate. Much like the Munro tables were not accurate and have been gradually updated over the years, so will the Peak Visibility Project along with the Horner and Traci classifications.
I will go into more detail over on the <a href="https://github.com/stevenhorner/PeakVisibility/" title="Peak Visibility Project on Github">Peak Visibility Github page</a> over the coming weeks, where you can also find much of the raw data and results but I&#8217;m going to take a little break from it, so don&#8217;t expect to to see full explanations in the next couple of days.</p>

<p>I Would like to thank Michael Spencer (<a href="http://scottishsnow.wordpress.com/" title="Scottishsnow">Scottishsnow</a>) for a few helpful pointers early on in the process and his <a href="http://scottishsnow.wordpress.com/2013/06/21/caleb-arthurs/" title="Caleb's List">Caleb&#8217;s List post</a> which gave me the spark I needed. His site is well worth following. I also need to thank or blame <a href="http://twitter.com/PhilOutdoors" title="Phil Turner">Phil Turner</a> who if he reads this will probably wonder why, he pointed out Schiehallion one winter while walking from Bridge of Orchy to Kinlochleven and mentioned it being one of the most visible mountains, that stuck.</p>

<p>I mentioned at the start that the most sucessful projects are those where you learn, in the course of this project I have worked with Virtualization, Ubuntu server, Ubuntu Desktop, QGIS (1.8, 2.0.1, 2.1.0), GDAL, GRASS, python, projections and a multitude of other stuff. I thoroughly enjoyed the process.</p>

<p>To produce the data and results I have used a variety of data from the following sources:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.hills-database.co.uk/" title="The Database of British and Irish Hills">The Database of British and Irish Hills</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.qgis.org/" title="QGIS">QGIS</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Maps on this page use Ordnance Survey OpenData which is © Crown copyright and database right 2013.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain Leader Training]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/09/07/mountain-leader-training/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-07T20:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/09/07/mountain-leader-training</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/ML2.JPG" alt="Training in Lake District" />Over a year ago now I attended a Mountain Leader Summer Training course with the intention of deciding if I would like to guide walks for a living. I had taken many friends and family walking over the years and wanted to know what it would be like to do it for a job.</p>

<p>If I decided not to follow that ML path the money (£450) wouldn&#8217;t be wasted because I knew I would gain new skills which I&#8217;m always eager to learn. I originally hoped to do the course at <a href="http://www.glenmorelodge.org.uk/" title="Glenmore Lodge">Glenmore Lodge</a>, having heard good things from others who had attended. Unfortunately they were fully booked, my next choice would be in the Lake District.</p>

<p>Top of the list was <a href="http://www.mountainleadercourses.co.uk/" title="Apex Training">Apex</a> not just because they begin with A, but because the prices were competitive, included accommodation in <a href="http://www.yha.org.uk/hostel/coniston-holly-how" title="Holly How Youth Hostel">Holly How Youth Hostel</a> where I had stayed before and they had good feedback on their courses.
Upon arrival at the Youth Hostel I checked in and waited for the others to arrive. The other attendees had a range of backgrounds and reasons for attending. I was surprised that some had never wildcamped a night in their lives.</p>

<h3>Entry Requirements</h3>

<p>To attend a <a href="http://www.mountain-training.org/default.aspx" title="Mountain Training">Mountain Leader</a> course you are supposed to have a minimum of 20 Quality mountain days, be registered with the <a href="http://www.mountain-training.org/default.aspx" title="Mountain Training">Mountain Training Association</a> in your country and have a log book completed to show that you have this experience.
I had typed my log book up and had over 40 quality mountain days from all over the UK, this was only a fraction of the quality days I could have actually entered.
Not everyone else was this organised or experienced, some had not completed the log book at all. Some clearly didn&#8217;t have anywhere near that level of experience.
<img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/ML4.jpg" alt="Log Book" /></p>

<h3>Numbers and Reasons</h3>

<p>There were 5 of us who arrived for the course on the Sunday evening, also Marc from <a href="http://www.passandpeak.com/" title="Pass and Peak">Pass and Peak</a> who is a qualified Mountain Leader tagged along to keep his hand in and helped out for the first few days. We were joined on the Tuesday by Dean from <a href="http://www.activeedge.co.uk/" title="Active Edge">Active Edge</a> who I had more in common with (not paragliding) but I will get to that shortly.</p>

<p>I already mentioned my reasons for attending but the other attendees generally had different reasons. Two were from the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/The-Glasgow-Walking-and-Hillwalking-Club/" title="Glasgow Walking and Hillwalking club">Glasgow hill walking club</a> and they wanted to learn skills to help with the group walks they did. Another attendee worked for the scouts, but was more of a climber. There was only one who was really doing the course for the mountain leader qualification so he could use that as part of his business as a paraglider teacher, this was Dean who joined us on the second day after having started a course previously and breaking an ankle.
There was 3 males and 3 females which I think is unusual, generally I believe the males outnumber the women.</p>

<h3>What do you learn?</h3>

<p>Below is a overview of the things we covered in my course, I can&#8217;t guarantee I got this in correct order, it was over a year since my course.</p>

<h4>Weather Forecasting</h4>

<p>The weather reading was really interesting and I learned a lot, I understood what an isobar was before the course but not much more. Each evening we spent time studying the next few days weather charts and making our predictions. We would also review what we had predicted for the previous day. This could sound dull to some, but I really enjoyed this and I now read the synoptic charts myself before heading to the hills as well as checking what <a href="http://www.mwis.org.uk/" title="Mountain Weather Information Service">MWIS</a> say.</p>

<h4>Navigation</h4>

<p>The first full day started with finding out our natural pacing by walking 100m and seeing how many steps it took. We then did compass work and map reading with lots of practise. While I could read a map well and had basic compass skills, this highlighted I needed more practise. We were each taught about a different plant that we would then have to point out to the others and explain more about it. The day finished back at the Youth Hostel with predicting the weather and reviewing our previous predictions.
<img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/ML1.JPG" alt="Practising" /></p>

<h4>Rope Work</h4>

<p>The second day was Rope work and steep ground, we also practised map and compass work. The rope work was another area I was keen to learn in, while I climbed indoors the techniques used on the Mountain Leader training is very different. We had fun trying out the different knots, altough you can get away with only one. You learn everything you need to lower someone down rock faces with only a rope and no other climbing equipment (we had helmets). Besides for the brushing up my map reading skills this was the most enjoyable part of the week. Again the day ends with the weather for the coming days and review.</p>

<h4>Rope practise &amp; Trip planning</h4>

<p>Day three we practised steep ground and crossed loose shale, again map and compass work. We then put our new skills from the rope lessons the day before to practise by setting up everything ourselves with the instructor checking just before we lowered each other. We then headed back to the Youth Hostel to do some planning work, this involved planning a trip for groups as if we were qualified mountain leaders. We would have to take into account the ability of the people we were given, the weather, the area, the desires of the group and a lot more. This was actually easier for me than the others because I knew the Lake District far better than the others but I don&#8217;t really like doing this. Again we finished with the weather.</p>

<h4>Overnighter</h4>

<p>Day four is the day we would be setting off for our overnighter, obviously to me this is nothing new but for several of the others this was a huge deal. One had never done a wildcamp before and it looked like from the size of her pack that she had brought the entire contents of her house. A slight exageration, I&#8217;m not sure she had practised pitching the tent she had borrowed either. Yes I took the Trailstar, you can imagine the others faces when I described it. Yet it wasn&#8217;t the only one in our group, Dean also had a Trailstar and had read my review and pitching guide for it. I wonder how often 2 Trailstars had been used on an ML course at that point.</p>

<p>The weather was poor when we headed out, I don&#8217;t think it stopped raining all day. We spent the day taking turns navigating the rest of the group to the locations we were given. You learn a lot more than just navigating but taking into account the groups abilities and pacing rather than racing off. After a wet day navigating we pitched our shelters, the instructor was keen to look at the Trailstar and was happy with it. I think he had visions of me and Dean having to share his tent with us. We then practised river crossings not in the river because it was in flood. A few hours rest before we had to get up for night nav.</p>

<h4>Night Nav</h4>

<p>This was another part of the course I was looking forward to, when we emerged from our shelters not only was it dark but the fog had descended and we could only see a few feet ahead of us. Perfect weather for really learning. We may as well have been blind folded the visibility was so poor, yet the rain had stopped. The streams were flooded and we had several to cross. I think all of us enjoyed the night nav, it&#8217;s the perfect way to put all skills learned earlier in the week to practise.</p>

<p>The final day we walked back to our pickup location which was at the Old Dungeeon Ghyll. We then returned to the Youth Hostel where we were individually debriefed by our instructor.</p>

<h4>Debrief</h4>

<p>The instructor was very happy with me over the week and with my levels of experience and knowledge. I didn&#8217;t have much I needed to work on, he commented on the depth of experience I already had. He did comment on footwear because during the week I had discussed my dislike for boots which I had worn all week. He said they had passed people with Trailrunners but while that might be fine for the guide, if you were actually leading you would probably want to wear boots so that your clients who have less or no experience wear boots that they should be safer in. He wore trailrunners when not working.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/ML3.jpg" alt="Bed Time Reading" /></p>

<h3>Reading</h3>

<p>While training to become a Summer Mountain Leader there are a couple of useful books that are worth reading:</p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0954151100/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0954151100&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21" title="Hill Walking: The Official Handbook of the Mountain Leader and Walking Group Leader Schemes">Hill Walking: The Official Handbook of the Mountain Leader and Walking Group Leader Schemes</a></li>
<li> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0907521932/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0907521932&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21" title="Hostile Habitats">Hostile Habitats</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The above are essential reading even if you have no interest in leading. The following 2 books are useful if you decide to go for the Winter Mountain leader or one of the climbing awards.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0954151135/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0954151135&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21" title="Winter Skills: Essential Walking and Climbing Techniques">Winter Skills: Essential Walking and Climbing Techniques</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/095415116X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=095415116X&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=faitocom-21" title="Rock Climbing: Essential Skills &amp; Techniques">Rock Climbing: Essential Skills &amp; Techniques</a></li>
</ul>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>I loved it, the people in my group had a wide variety of skill levels but all were there to learn and no one dropped out. I decided not to persue a career Leading. I will continue to take friends and family out walking but I would hate the planning side that I would need to do if taking paying customers, which is strange considering how much I love maps. I would just prefer not to have the hassle, I go walking to get away from things not to take more potential problems with me.</p>

<p>While we were doing the Mountain Leader Training there was was an Assessment course running at the same time. It was interesting to talk to them and It was obvious to me some of them didn&#8217;t have the skills to be a leader. Only 1 passed out 5.</p>

<p>I would highly recommend going on the course even if you have no intention of taking the assessment and becoming a leader. The skills you will learn and refine during the week are worth every penny.</p>

<p>Unfortunately I forgot to take many pictures during the course and the ones I did take are very poor quality. Sorry about that.</p>

<h4>Be aware that there have been changes to the course since I attended, the rope work has changed considerably. <a href="http://www.mountain-training.org/latest-news/mountain-leader-summer-award-updates" title="Changes to Summer Mountain Leader Training">Please read this</a>.</h4>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Most Visible Mountain in Scotland]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/08/30/the-most-visible-mountain-in-scotland/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T18:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/08/30/the-most-visible-mountain-in-scotland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/Schiehallion_viewshed.jpg" alt="Schiehallion Viewshed" /></p>

<p>On a recent trip to the West Highlands I pointed out what I believed to be Schiehallion in the distance as we crossed Rannoch Moor in the car. I recalled how I had been told it was the mountain you could see from the most places in Scotland.
I decided that I would test if this was really true. I had a feeling it wasn&#8217;t.</p>

<h3>How do you do that?</h3>

<p>Obviously I am not going to stand in every spot in Scotland and work out what mountains I can see, I would need several life times. Instead I will use <a href="http://www.qgis.org/" title="Quantum GIS">Quantum GIS (QGIS)</a> on a computer along with elevation data and a handy plugin or 2. I had recently read <a href="https://twitter.com/MikeRSpencer" title="Michael Spencer on Twitter">Michael Spencers</a> <a href="http://scottishsnow.wordpress.com/2013/06/21/caleb-arthurs/" title="Caleb's List">blog post</a> regarding <a href="http://scottishsnow.wordpress.com/2013/06/21/caleb-arthurs/" title="Caleb's List">Caleb&#8217;s List</a> which gave some helpful information, have a look at what it <a href="http://scottishsnow.wordpress.com/2013/06/21/caleb-arthurs/" title="Caleb's List">viewable from Arthurs Seat</a>.</p>

<h3>This could take a long time&#8230;</h3>

<p>I said I would need several life times to do this without a computer, but even using a standard computer it takes a long time. I worked out how far to the horizon and I would work out my calcuation based on seeing the top of the mountain, or more accurately someone stood on the top.
My first run with the full data took 2.5 days just to work out where in Scotland you could view someone stood on the top of Schiehallion. When I looked at the data annoyingly it hadn&#8217;t done it correctly and half of the data was missing. Here&#8217;s what was produced.
Remember I wanted to find out which mountain was the most visible in Scotland, within my criteria which you can read in the Additional Technical Details further down this post. I decided to limit the mountains to only Munros initially, this would mean that I have to run the same process that I tried on Schiehallion for each Munro.</p>

<pre><code>2.5 days * 282 Munros = A long time (705 days)
</code></pre>

<p>I am not the most patient person, 2015 for an answer is more than I am willing to wait.</p>

<h3>Additional Technical Details</h3>

<h4>Software used:</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.qgis.org/" title="Quantum GIS">Quantum GIS</a></li>
<li><a href="http://pyqgis.org/repo/contributed" title="QGIS Visibility Analysis">Visibility Analysis plugin</a></li>
<li><a href="http://grass.osgeo.org/grass64/manuals/r.los.html" title="r.los GRASS module">r.los GRASS module</a></li>
</ul>


<h4>Data used:</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-and-government/products/terrain-50.html" title="OS Terrain 50">OS Terrain 50</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-and-government/products/boundary-line.html" title="OS Boundary-Line">OS Boundry-line</a></li>
</ul>


<h4>Extra data needed for calculation:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Calculated horizon: 90 miles (from Ben Nevis)</li>
<li>Limit to only the 282 Munros</li>
</ul>


<p>The software used was <a href="http://www.qgis.org/" title="Quantum GIS">Quantum GIS (QGIS)</a>, I tried both the <a href="http://pyqgis.org/repo/contributed" title="QGIS Visibility Analysis">QGIS Visibility Analysis plugin</a> and the <a href="http://grass.osgeo.org/grass64/manuals/r.los.html" title="r.los GRASS module">GRASS Line of Sight (r.los) module</a> within the Sextante plugin.</p>

<p>The Terrain data is <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-and-government/products/terrain-50.html" title="OS Terrain 50">OS Terrain 50</a> Grid which I merged together to produce one large terrain TIF for Scotland, I then clipped this using the Scottish boundary (probably didn&#8217;t need to do this).</p>

<p>I used <a href="http://www.boatsafe.com/tools/horizon.htm" title="Boatsafe Horizon Calculator">Boatsafe website</a> to calculate the horizon. This is different depending on your height, if you are stood on the top of Ben Nevis obviously you can see further than if you were at sea level. I decided to use 2 metres above the height of Ben Nevis, 1346m for all mountains. This calculated that the horizon would be just under 90 miles away, which I rounded up to 90. In reality the chances of actually being able to see that far are almost zero.</p>

<p>I also decided that I would use the following scenario, that if someone stood on the top of a mountain could they be seen within 90 miles without the direct line of sight being blocked by other hills. I have no way to calcuate trees or man made structures blocking the view and this would only increase the time taken to calculate.</p>

<p>The QGIS Visibility Analysis took 2.5 days to complete on my Core i5 3.2Ghz with 8GB RAM machine. Annoying <a href="http://www.qgis.org/" title="Quantum GIS">QGIS</a> is only a 32 bit program and only uses a single core rather than the 4 available. For some reason it didn&#8217;t complete correctly, but even with half of the results it was still interesting to see how far away Schiehallion can potentially be seen.</p>

<p>I decided to try the <a href="http://grass.osgeo.org/grass64/manuals/r.los.html" title="r.los GRASS module">GRASS line of sight (r.los) module</a> in the <a href="http://sextantegis.com/" title="Sextante">Sextante plugin</a>. I have found GRASS to be faster in the past than some of the built-in functions. This time I ran a test with a 25 mile view and this completed in 10 minutes.
Running the full 90 mile range in GRASS took 20 hours, the image at the top of this post is the returned data overlaid on Google Terrain.</p>

<p>To complete this using <a href="http://grass.osgeo.org/grass64/manuals/r.los.html" title="r.los GRASS module">r.los</a> is still going to take 235 days, unless I can build a multi-threaded version of QGIS (<a href="http://faunaliagis.wordpress.com/2013/08/26/qgis-64bit-for-windows-is-ready-to-test/" title="64bit QGIS">64 bit test version</a>, not mulithreaded just released). This isn&#8217;t planned until at least version 2.1, 2.0 is the next release. In the interim I will test with different viewable distances to find an acceptable processing time. The full 90 miles is further than anyone realistically could ever see anyway.</p>

<p>Once each mountains visibility is calculated, I convert the raster output to vector, crop using the Scottish Boundary-line data (removes visility at sea) then calculate the total area. This gives an easy figure to compare between each mountain. This figure could then be given as a percentage of the total area of Scotland eg.</p>

<pre><code>Schiehallion is visible from 0.0105% of Scotland.
</code></pre>

<p>I have also ran the above for Ben Nevis which can be seen below</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/BenNevis_Viewable.jpg" alt="Ben Nevis Viewshed" /></p>

<pre><code>Ben Nevis is visible from 0.0151% of Scotland
</code></pre>

<p>You can already see if the above is correct Ben Nevis is viewable from a larger percentage of Scotland. I think other mountains maybe more visible than Ben Nevis.</p>

<h3>The Most Visible Mountains (So far)..</h3>

<ol>
<li>Ben Nevis (0.0151%)</li>
<li>Schiehallion (0.0105%)</li>
<li>TBC&#8230;</li>
</ol>


<h3>Fixes</h3>

<p>After generating the Ben Nevis and Schiehallion data I realised a couple of potential errors. I had calculated the Horizon from the top of Ben Nevis and used this for Schiehallion too, 261m higher than it actually is although this wouldn&#8217;t actually alter the end results (Schiehallions height is used for the calcuation). Originally I used the <a href="http://pyqgis.org/repo/contributed" title="QGIS Visibility Analysis">QGIS visibility plugin</a> which doesn&#8217;t allow for the Earth&#8217;s curvature (I don&#8217;t think), <a href="http://grass.osgeo.org/grass64/manuals/r.los.html" title="r.los GRASS module">r.los</a> does allow me to choose this. I will re-run both Schiehallion and Ben Nevis without limiting the viewable range and enable the Earths curvature.</p>

<p>Ben Dolphin (<a href="https://twitter.com/CountrysideBen" title="Ben Dolphin">@CountrysideBen</a>) pointed out an excellent site <a href="http://www.viewfinderpanoramas.org/panoramas.html" title="Panoramas">Panoramas</a> where you can view and download computer generated Panoramas of many mountains around the world, including Scotland. They are fantastic and happily the Ben Nevis ones look very close to my findings.</p>

<h3>Help and suggestions</h3>

<p>I am not a mathematician, geographer, cartographer or scientist just someone who loves mountains, maps and computers. I would be very surprised if I haven&#8217;t made many mistakes in my calculations. If you are aware of any, please let me know or if you can provide any help. I find it fascinating and hope others do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Maps]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/08/26/open-maps/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T21:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/08/26/open-maps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/BenNevisOSMCycle1.jpg" alt="Ben Nevis OpenCycleMap" />
Following on from my <a href="http://stevenhorner.com/blog/2013/08/18/map-subscription-service/" title="StevenHorner.com - Map Subscription Service">previous post</a> and the desire for an official map subscription service, I mentioned if the established map providers don&#8217;t do something radical soon they will start to lose business among the regular public.
The biggest threat to traditional mapping agencies like <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> or <a href="http://www.ign.fr/" title="IGN">IGN</a> I believe will come from <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> based maps. Several years ago I remember seeing <a href="http://www.opencyclemap.org/" title="OpenCycleMap">OpenCycleMap</a> with it&#8217;s contour lines and relief shading which look very similar to <a href="http://www.harveymaps.co.uk/" title="Harvey Maps">Harvey maps</a>. The problem with <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> at the moment depending on the area you are looking at is the holes in the data.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/BenNevisOSMLandscape1.jpg" alt="Ben Nevis Thunderforest Landcape Map" /></p>

<h3>Holes in the data?</h3>

<p>Although <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> started in the UK it is a truely worldwide map. In many less developed countries and many developed ones too, <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> is far more accurate and complete than any other map available. Yet if you look at many areas in the UK, things are missing. To use for walking purposes the standard Mapnik layer isn&#8217;t much good unless you are navigating towns and villages.
If you want to walk in the hills you need contours, those orange swirly lines on <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> maps. I said above the <a href="http://www.opencyclemap.org/" title="OpenCycleMap">OpenCycleMap</a> caught my eye, it is basically just the <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> data styled differently with contours and relief shading added. There are other syles available that also offer Contours like Thunderforest Outdoors or Thunderforest Landscape. These omit much of the data from the standard map that you don&#8217;t need for outdoor activities but keep things like pubs and toilets.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/BenNevisOSMOutdoors1.jpg" alt="Ben Nevis ThunderForest Outdoors Map" /></p>

<h3>Dangerous</h3>

<p>You would think that the Outdoors style would be the one to go for, but take a look at Ben Nevis. It has contours but those contours are STRM (Shuttle Radar Topography Mission) ones that dont&#8217; show the vertical drop if you wandered too far from the summit. They only show contours every 90m in the UK, 30m in the USA. In fact it doesn&#8217;t look a bad descent.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/BenNevisOSMB006.jpg" alt="Ben Nevis Summit ThunderForest Landscape Map" /></p>

<p>Take a look at the Landscape style and it adds the vertical drop marked with the solid black line, much like Harvey maps show. Although still those contours are used that just aren&#8217;t detailed enough. There are areas where the contours don&#8217;t join up correctly either. Also the Outdoors map oddly omits walls, which I always find help greatly with navigation.
I&#8217;m not exactly selling <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> for walking if it&#8217;s missing potentially lethal vertical drops. The beauty of <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OSM</a> is you can use the data and style it in anyway you like and add other data to create a totally unique map that has the details YOU want.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/BenNevisOSMB002.jpg" alt="OS OpenData Terrain 50 - Ben Nevis Contours" /></p>

<h3>What data is available</h3>

<p>If you live in the UK <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> have released some &#8220;OpenData&#8221; which you can use. They actually released several complete maps but none of these are ideal for walking, they kept the Crown Jewels (Explorer &amp; Landranger). The products that are usefull to supplement <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-and-government/products/terrain-50.html" title="OS OpenData Terrain 50">OS Terrain 50</a> (replacing LAND-FORM Panorama)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-and-government/products/vectormap-district.html" title="OS VectorMap District">VectorMap District</a></li>
</ul>


<p>VectorMap district is actually an entire map product but we can borrow only the bits we need.
There are a lot of other sources of data out there for the UK and overseas. <a href="http://www.gis.naturalengland.org.uk/pubs/gis/GIS_register.asp" title="Natural England Data sets">Natural England</a> provide Open Access land data, so you could re-create those shaded orange areas. They provide a lot other data too but most is not needed on a walking map.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/BenNevisOSMB003.jpg" alt="Bodged together Map" /></p>

<h3>So what can we create?</h3>

<p>Here&#8217;s a very quick bodged together map just to see what this data looks like, you can see it&#8217;s bodged together because it&#8217;s not layered correctly and it looks to be honest horrendous, but you can see if it was styled, it would have everything we need. Ths was created in a couple of minutes using <a href="http://www.qgis.org/" title="Quantum GIS">Quantum GIS( QGIS)</a>, to do this properly and produce a usable map at the end I prefer other tools. In the next post I will explain how to create a usable Outdoors maps using the data mentioned above.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Map Subscription Service?]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/08/18/map-subscription-service/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-18T22:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2013/08/18/map-subscription-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/MapNoService.jpg" alt="No Map Service For You!" /></p>

<p>Over the last year I have been thinking about maps a lot, from using them in my day job, planning adventures in my spare time and for future job plans. Living in the UK the most obvious maps to use are from <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> and anyone who has even the most fleeting use for a map will generally be familiar with some of their maps. The paper <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/s/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;field-keywords=explorer%20lake%20district&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Aexplorer%20lake%20district&amp;sprefix=explorer%20lake%20%2Caps%2C169&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;url=search-alias%3Daps" title="OS Lake District Maps">Explorer maps of the Lake District</a> that I keep in the boot of my car are looking very worn, although these days they rarely leave the boot. Why do they rarely leave their home?</p>

<p>Like most online outdoor walkers and bloggers I have used digital mapping for years, but always carry a paper map in case my digital device breaks or runs out of power. I rarely look at my paper map unless I want an overview of an area. Generally in somewhere like the Lake District I can recognise most of the landmarks and hills I can see around me. The map I generally have in my pack for this isn&#8217;t an Ordnance Survey map but the <a href="http://rcm-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/e/cm?lt1=_blank&amp;bc1=000000&amp;IS2=1&amp;bg1=FFFFFF&amp;fc1=000000&amp;lc1=0000FF&amp;t=faitocom-21&amp;o=2&amp;p=8&amp;l=as4&amp;m=amazon&amp;f=ifr&amp;ref=ss_til&amp;asins=1851374671" title="Harvey Lake District Map">Harveys Lake District map</a>, yet this rarely leaves my pack either these days. All of this will be familiar to many outdoor enthusiasts who are embracing modern technology and using Digital mapping more and more.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/HarveyLakeDistrict.jpg" alt="Harvey Lake District Map" /></p>

<p>There are problems with digital mapping and I don&#8217;t mean running out of juice in your GPS device or smartphone. I&#8217;m talking about &#8220;Digital Map Lock In&#8221;, this is the most frustrating and frankly old fashioned thing about digital maps.</p>

<h3>What is Digital Map Lock In?</h3>

<p>In the UK the biggest provider of outdoor mapping data is <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a>, many (UK people probably) believe them to produce the finest maps in the world. These are the maps used by the majority of people walking in the UK both paper based and digital. Yet due to the way <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> licence, restrict and distribute their digital data they have produced and seam to actively encourage each company who uses their maps to produce outdoor mapping programs like <a href="http://www.memory-map.co.uk/" title="Memory-map">Memory-Map</a>, <a href="http://www.routebuddy.com/" title="RouteBuddy">Route Buddy</a>, <a href="http://www.anquet.com/" title="Anquet">Anquet</a> or Mobile specific apps like <a href="http://www.viewranger.com/" title="Viewranger">Viewranger</a> to create their own map format. Their map formats are &#8220;locked&#8221; to their program.</p>

<p>If I buy a digital map for <a href="http://www.memory-map.co.uk/" title="Memory-map">Memory-Map</a>, I can only use it in that program not in <a href="http://www.anquet.com/" title="Anquet">Anquet</a> or anything else. This sounds very familiar to digital music a few years ago, the songs were locked to iTunes or <a href="http://www.napster.com/" title="Napster">Napster</a> (legal version). If you wanted to play them in anything else you were out of luck. Unless you did a little <a href="http://digiex.net/downloads/download-center-2-0/applications/11796-requiem-4-1-remove-itunes-drm-fairplay-music-video-books.html" title="Remove Apple DRM">research</a> and broke the law removing the Digital Rights Management (DRM). What did people do? They downloaded MP3s illegally, the music industry tried taking people to court and dishing out massive fines but did it work, No!</p>

<p>Eventually some of the music industry realised that things were/are changing, the models of old were crumbling and that their old model didn&#8217;t fit with todays generation. <a href="http://www.spotify.com" title="Spotify">Spotify</a> and similar services have appeared that offer consumers everything they had with their illegal sources (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Napster" title="Wikipedia - Napster">Napster</a>, <a href="http://www.limewire.com/" title="Limewire">Limewire</a>, etc) almost any song they desire in one convenient place and available on any device. People like myself were happy to pay for the service and I have done so every month since the first mobile app was released (3 years ago?). This model still has DRM with its restrictions, but I am happy to pay for it because I can listen to my music on everything I currently use (phone, computers, we browser and even now in programs like <a href="http://xbmc.org/" title="XBMC">XBMC</a>). I like the all I can eat model with the choice of millions of songs rather than the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/MP3-Music-Download/b/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;node=77197031&amp;tag=faitocom-21" title="Amazon MP3 Store">Amazon model</a> of no DRM but paying for each song model. Who has made the most money from me, <a href="http://www.spotify.com" title="Spotify">Spotify</a> by a mile (£9.99/month for 3+ years).</p>

<h3>All You Can Eat Maps</h3>

<p>So what has all this talk of music got to do with maps, well we need the same thing to happen with digital maps. I don&#8217;t want to be stuck using <a href="http://www.memory-map.co.uk/" title="Memory-map">Memory-Map</a> because I chose to buy a map from them 3 years ago or pay <a href="http://www.viewranger.com/" title="Viewranger">Viewranger</a> for the same area again to use it in their app. I want to pay for my <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> maps and be able to use them in any program or service and they be constantly up to date. I have no doubt someone is sat there thinking but you can&#8217;t do that with paper maps. Exactly that&#8217;s old fashioned and exactly the problem we have, we want new ideas not old ones.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mapping-Evolution-2011-009.jpg" alt="MM Tracker &amp; Memory-Map" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;m sure someone else would point out that <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> provide an app for iPhone(<a href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/os-mapfinder/id577097874?mt=8" title="OS MapFinder">OS Map Finder</a>). I think this is the wrong move, I want Ordnance Survey to be the map producers and distributors with other companies providing software and services that use their data. I am happy to pay for a program or service and I have for <a href="http://alpinequest.psyberia.net/" title="AlpineQuest">AlpineQuest</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/mmtrackerinfo/" title="MM Tracker">MM Tracker</a>, <a href="http://osmand.net/" title="OsmAnd">OSMand+</a> and many others.</p>

<p>What I would like is to pay a small monthly fee to have <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> maps available in any program and always up to date. <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> actually do already provide this service for business users, its called <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-and-government/products/os-ondemand/index.html" title="OS OnDemand">OS OnDemand</a> and it starts from £1,500 rising to £20,000 per year. Slightly out of reach of the normal outdoor enthusiast. What I believe <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> should do is offer a subscription map service for around £5 per month, this would allow me full access to their digital maps (possibly excluding MasterMap). They would provide the service and allow me to allow apps and services to use my subscription in the same way you approve access to your Twitter or Google account. This would provide an extra revenue stream for them, £60 per year from me and likely every other digital map user. This would mean apps like <a href="http://www.viewranger.com/" title="Viewranger">Viewranger</a> would need to charge for their app again, I paid for at least one version of their app already.</p>

<p>Obviously the service would have to allow caching of maps, otherwise the service would be useless in remote areas. Providing always up to date maps at each scale and for the whole of the UK is the incentive that would encourage users to constantly subscribe.</p>

<h3>Why would Ordnance Survey do this?</h3>

<p>In recent years <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> have generally had UK mapping to themselves other than the areas <a href="http://www.harveymaps.co.uk/" title="Harvey Maps">Harvey Maps</a> provide, but the average person likely has not seen or used them. I have only seen them available digitally for one program (even worse than OS). There is also a new kid on the block, actually its not that new. <a href="http://http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap (OSM)</a> is celebrating its 9th year, but it is only recently that it is starting to become a realistic alternative to other major map providers like Ordnance Survey or Google for online maps. You may scoff at the thought of navigating the Cairngorms with an <a href="http://http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a>, but I believe its now almost possible if combined with contours and a grid.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/landscape.jpg" alt="Thunderforest Landscape Map" /></p>

<p>Anyone who has attended a mountain leader course will have navigated largely using contours. <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/s/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;field-keywords=explorer%20lake%20district&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Aexplorer%20lake%20district&amp;sprefix=explorer%20lake%20%2Caps%2C169&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;url=search-alias%3Daps" title="OS Lake District Maps">Ordnance Survey Explorer</a> maps can be very &#8220;busy&#8221; once you learn to use contours correctly. Take a look at <a href="http://www.thunderforest.com/" title="Thunderforest">Thunderforest</a> <a href="http://www.thunderforest.com/landscape/" title="Thunderforest Landscape">Landscape</a> and <a href="http://www.thunderforest.com/outdoors/" title="Thunderforest Outdoors">Outdoor</a> maps for examples that use <a href="http://http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OSM</a> data. They are still missing a few things in my opinion but the designer of those styles chose to omit some things like walls and fences. The biggest thing <a href="http://http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> has going for it is that it is open and the data is freely available to use by anyone and can be updated by anyone. So if something is missing go and add it. I don&#8217;t know about you, but I have spotted loads of mistakes on OS maps (intentional or otherwise) it can also take years for things to be added or removed. Not only should <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> be worried but so should Google, they already borrowed <a href="http://http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OSMs</a> model and now allow you to make updates to their maps using <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/mapmaker" title="Google Map Maker">Google Map Maker</a>. I am digressing, some of these thoughts will likely be discussed in future posts.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2657852/website/images/OSVectorMapDistrict.jpg" alt="OS VectorMap District" /></p>

<p>So returning to that question, why would <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> do this. Well they could and should provide a service like this now, rather than waiting until <a href="http://http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> have eaten away at their business. If they provided this service now I believe they would be opening up an untapped revenue stream and would be a leader once again. Almost all of the mobile apps available already provide <a href="http://http://www.openstreetmap.org/" title="OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</a> as well as Ordnance Survey. If the free data becomes as good or better why would you pay?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/" title="Ordnance Survey">Ordnance Survey</a> needs to provide something that no one else can (currently) offer, don&#8217;t forget there is already free &#8221;<a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/business-and-government/products/opendata-products.html" title="OS OpenData">OpenData</a>&#8221; release by Ordnance Survey that when combined with other free sources of data is potentially far better than what we currently pay for, keep an eye out for future posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Website: Finally]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/12/17/new-website-finally/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-17T19:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/12/17/new-website-finally</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Finally I have moved to a new host <a href="http://www.github.com">(Github)</a> and away from <a href="http://www.wordpress.com">Wordpress</a> to <a href="http://www.octopress.org">Octopress</a>. This process started almost 12 months ago, but I am now almost finished. A lot of hard decisions have been made regarding the site, what to keep and what to remove. There is still a new theme to create but I didn&#8217;t want to delay any longer.</p>

<h3>Old Links to StevenHorner.com</h3>

<p>I won&#8217;t get into the technical side of it but I made a decision a lot of years ago that resulted in the inability to forward links to the new site. My advice to anyone setting up a site, enable permalinks.<br/>
Old links from external sites will take you to a custom error page which has links to the most popular posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/blog/2010/09/19/mld-trailstar-review/">MLD Trailstar Review</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/blog/2010/09/22/mld-trailstar-pitching-guide/">MLD Trailstar Pitching Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/blog/2011/03/05/montane-lite-speed-h2o-jacket-review/">Montane Lite-Speed H2O Jacket Review</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/blog/2010/10/31/routes-my-way/">Routes: My Way</a></li>
</ul>


<h3>RSS Feed</h3>

<p>If you subscribed to the RSS Feed for the site this also will no longer work, this time it&#8217;s not me but Google who have stopped supporting Feedburner. If like me, you love RSS Feeds you can resubscribe by using the link at the top right of the site.</p>

<h3>So why the change &amp; the delay?</h3>

<p>I was sick of the site running slowly, which was the result partly of the host <a href="http://www.godaddy.com">(Godaddy)</a>, the platform <a href="http://www.wordpress.com">(Wordpress)</a> and my configuration of the site. The delay was mainly due to exporting the posts from the Wordpress and losing all the formatting, but the old posts are migrated. What this means is that I can now concentrate on new content, the delay to migrating the site has resulted in 0 posts in the last 6 months. There are several new posts either written or almost complete. I am looking forward to regularly posting again.</p>

<p>Apologies for the disruption, hopefully due to the design of the new site this should not happen again. If you spot any links that do not work or errors please let me know and I will fix them as soon as I can.</p>

<h3>Update 18th August 2013</h3>

<p>Another 8 months and nothing posted. There have been lots of reasons from drive failures and loss of completed posts to back problems and whole host of other things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kitty's Wood & Public Rights Of Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/06/06/kittys-wood-public-rights-of-way/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-06T19:00:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/06/06/kittys-wood-public-rights-of-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/B2-Blocked-A.jpg" alt="Footpath Blocked" /></p>

<p>Something is stirring in many small villages and towns throughout England &amp; Wales. In normally quiet villages, people are angrily discussing the latest happenings in the woods and fields around them. People who normally keep themselves to themselves are beginning to stand up and share their voice. So what&#8217;s causing these normally quiet villagers to break their silence?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In a word &#8220;Access&#8221; or Public Rights of Way (PROW), in England &amp; Wales there are around 140,000 miles of off-road routes that are classed as Public Rights of Way (PROW), that&#8217;s over 5.5 times around the earth. These are shown on Ordnance Survey Explorer maps in green and Landranger maps in red. To be classified as a PROW a route needs to appear on the &#8220;Definitive maps&#8221; held by the local authorities. This then means that you legally have a right to use the route and the landowner should not obstruct or divert it (<a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/info/britain/access-for-walkers-in-britain">see Ramblers page for more information</a>). So why are people becoming angry if they have 140,000 miles of paths to walk. In 2000 the government introduced The Countryside and Rights of Way Act which contained a cut-off date of 1 January 2026 for rights of way not on definitive maps. After this date those paths will be lost to public use. There have been estimates that up to half the walked paths in England &amp; Wales are not recorded. You could find a path that has been walked for generations suddenly lost. 2026 may sound a long way off but add to the fact that almost all local authorities have a backlog of years to add these paths. According to <a href="http://www.grough.co.uk/magazine/2012/05/14/access-group-welcomes-government-plans-to-update-lost-paths-on-maps">Grough</a>, Staffordshire County Council has a 17 year backlog which is set to get worse. Suddenly 2026 isn&#8217;t so far away.</p>

<p>Most of us, myself included don&#8217;t pay too much attention to reports like these until we feel the effects ourselves. Then suddenly there&#8217;s a wake up call, in my case paths I have walked since I first put one foot in front of the other are suddenly barbed wired across and blocked off. I live in a small village in County Durham called Roddymoor, to the South of the village there are woods known as &#8220;Kitty&#8217;s Wood&#8221;, which previously was the site of mining and a coke works. These were landscaped over in the late 1960&#8217;s and the wood was planted and footpaths put in.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/B2-Blocked-B.jpg" alt="Footpath and Stile blocked" /></p>

<p>The land was owned by <a href="http://www.durham.gov.uk/">Durham County Council</a> and leased as Roddymoor Farm and the paths were maintained by the Farm and the Council. Locals from Roddymoor, Crook, Billy Row and the surrounding area walked these paths for decades with no problems. The farm closed a few years ago and the Council took back management of the land, who in these budget cutting times decided to sell the land. The land was put up for auction in 2012 and eventually the land was sold to a few buyers, Kitty&#8217;s Woods included. Shortly after this problems started arising.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/C1-Blocked-A.jpg" alt="Stile &amp; Path Blocked" /></p>

<p>Paths were suddenly blocked with barbed wire and felled trees, walkers became angry and contacted the Council. They were told the paths were not PROW and did not appear on the &#8220;Definitive Map&#8221;, the new landowner was perfectly in his rights to close the paths they had. This will be the first time most will of heard of PROW, Definitive maps, etc. now what do they do. There are still some official PROW through the wood but less than half of the ones people have walked for over 40 years.</p>

<p>I will stress here the new landowner has done nothing wrong, the paths which are on the Definitive maps are open. The Council also can&#8217;t do anything now about these paths, unless they are added to the &#8220;Definitive map&#8221;. The annoying thing to many who have walked these, is that the Council did maintain them, owned the land and never prevented anyone. They could have and should have added the paths as PROW years ago but we can only deal with the present situation.</p>

<p><strong>So what can you do now?</strong></p>

<p>The only option open to walkers prevented access is to fill out a &#8220;Public Right of Way User Evidence Form&#8221; for each path, along with any details you can provide. For a path to be added to the &#8220;Definitive map&#8221; it needs to be have been used for over 20 years. The Council need as many people to fill these out as possible providing as many details as you can. The forms are a nightmare to complete and most would look at requests for grid references and copies of maps and give up. It has taken days to fill out the forms. To make it easier for anyone with no access to mapping or any idea how to find grid references I have provided the forms below to download for each path with the grid references completed and the map with route drawn on. You can download and draw on these, adding any details you like. These should make the process a lot quicker. If you would like a blank form <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/User_evidence_form.pdf">click here</a> (Impossible to find on the Council site?)</p>

<p><a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/OverviewMapLarge.jpg"><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/OverviewMapLarge.jpg" alt="Kitty's Wood Path Overview Map" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Key to Map:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Black dashed line = Existing PROW</li>
<li>Red dashed line = Path NOT marked as PROW</li>
<li>Purple dashed line = Existing PROW footpath should be bridleway (my opinion)</li>
</ul>


<p>The Downloads below will hopefully be helpful and save time, the path names are made up for my use to reference them. See overview map to help identify which path is which, click the image to make it larger.</p>

<p><strong>Downloads:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/OverviewMap.pdf">Kitty&#8217;s Wood Path Overview Map</a> &lt;&#8211; Above map as a PDF</li>
<li><a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/User_evidence_form.pdf">Blank Form</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/Definitive_Map_extract.pdf">Durham County Council Definitive Map Extract</a></li>
<li>Path B2 <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathB2Form.pdf">Form</a> &amp; <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathB2Map.pdf">Map</a></li>
<li>Path C1 <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathC1Form.pdf">Form</a> &amp; <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathC1Map.pdf">Map</a></li>
<li>Path E1 <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathE1Form.pdf">Form</a> &amp; <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathE1Map.pdf">Map</a></li>
<li>Path F1 <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathF1Form.pdf">Form</a> &amp; <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathF1Map.pdf">Map</a></li>
<li>Path F1B <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathF1BForm.pdf">Form </a> &amp; <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathF1BMap.pdf">Map</a></li>
<li>Path H1 <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathH1Form.pdf">Form</a> &amp; <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/PathH1Map.pdf">Map</a></li>
<li>Existing Path 43 <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/Path43Form.pdf">Form</a> &amp; <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/files/Path43Map.pdf">Map</a> &lt;&#8211;Should be a Bridleway</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Further Information:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://northernpies.blogspot.co.uk/2012/06/trouble-in-kittys-wood.html">Mike Knipe recent post on Kitty&#8217;s Wood</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.durham.gov.uk/Pages/prow.aspx">Durham County Councils Online Definitive Map</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.durham.gov.uk/Pages/Service.aspx?ServiceId=613">Durham County Councils PROW section</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/Volunteer/News/ROWconsultation">The Ramblers - Don&#8217;t Lose Your Way Campaign</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/mediacentre/archive/2003/crimepaths">The Ramblers - DEFRA and public rights of way</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/info/britain/access-for-walkers-in-britain">The Ramblers - Access for Walkers</a> &lt;&#8211; Good overview article</li>
<li><a href="http://www.grough.co.uk/magazine/2012/05/14/access-group-welcomes-government-plans-to-update-lost-paths-on-maps">Grough - Access group welcomes Government plans to update lost paths on maps</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.grough.co.uk/magazine/2010/03/25/paths-face-extinction-unless-government-adopts-plan">Grough - Paths face extinction unless Government adopts plan</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deerstalker 2012 Run - A Muddy Romp]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/04/27/deerstalker-2012-run-a-muddy-romp/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-27T21:05:50+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/04/27/deerstalker-2012-run-a-muddy-romp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/41153510" width="1024" height="575" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>I finally returned several years after running the first Deerstalker 5k, this time talking Traci into running it with me. Watch the video above for an idea of the fun had, the HD version is better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A First Year Walking - Traci]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/22/a-first-year-walking-traci/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-22T22:42:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/22/a-first-year-walking-traci</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lots of outdoors bloggers have been featuring guest posts over the last year. I thought it would be a good idea to ask <a href="http://www.twitter.com/traci_howarth">Traci</a> (my other half) to write about her first real year walking in the outdoors. It&#8217;s all totally new to her&#8230;over to <a href="http://www.twitter.com/traci_howarth">Traci</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-June-2011-051.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Up until April 2011 Saturdays and Sundays were spent in the local getting drunk and having hangovers for work on a Monday. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Striding-Edge-Swirral-Edge-April-2011-050.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>After meeting Steven in the February things started to gradually change. After my first walk in March to the Elephant trees in Weardale with him, then trying to take two of my kids on the same walk a few weeks later and getting lost in torrential rain. Luckily Steven was following to get us on the right track. I then went with him and walked up the Langdales Pikes (how sad, not knowing there would be water on the path haha). Then Striding Edge which I couldn&#8217;t understand why people were walking along the side instead of the ridge, which is all part of the fun. Coming down Catstye Cam we were skidding down a steep bank of scree, watched by a couple, bet they thought we were mad.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Glaramara-and-Allen-Crags-065.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Glaramara and Allen crags were next, after walking up a steep bank to a gate then sitting down to take my jacket off because I was hot, there was an awful smell. Steven said it was me, yeah right. After sitting for a few minutes resting we looked down at our feet and there was a dead sheep hence the smell haha blind as bats. As we got further up Steven decided he was going to run to the top of another small mountain no way was I, so I waited sheltering from the wind, which was blustery on the top. Coming down we ran, Steven had his buff on his head. He looked exactly like the roadrunner haha. To cool off we paddled in deep pools, where Steven got a drink in his kuksa from a waterfall.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-June-2011-056.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> After walking in the lakes, Steven took me to Scotland camping for his birthday in June. Ben Nevis and the CMD arete was my next challenge. We walked a different way to everyone else wading through heather and been attacked by millions of flies it was a hot day, so really hard going. I didnt have the energy to talk, which probably pleased Steven. As we started climbing up to Cairn Mor Dearg there was an old woman, I was really impressed she had got that far, I was really tired by then and had to climb up to Ben Nevis after that. The CMD arete was great to climb, loved every minute of it, although it was hard work i dont know where the CMD arete ended and Ben Nevis began. I just know climbing the last bit to Ben Nevis was really steep and cloud started covering everything behind us, was quiet eeiry (save yourself i shouted to him haha) not long after we reached the top we had a rest and something to eat before setting off to walk back down the tourist route. It&#8217;s a strange mountain, red hot walking up, got a bit sunburn on my neck, really cold and windy on the top, then not long after we set off to walk back down there was a large patch of snow. Pleased we didn&#8217;t walk up that way though, it was quite boring.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-June-2011-099.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> July and Scafell Pike the highest mountain in England, lots of people about and Stevens fall haha (not funny Traci). Not a very memorable mountain apart from the fall, we walked to the top, remember my knees hurting on the way down and an ignorant group of foreign young people who had their packs blocking the path on the way down so it was hard to get round, thats when Steven wobbled on a boulder and fell off, god my sides were aching with laughing he hurt his knee in the process, think he got a bit sick of me as I laughed all the way back to the car.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-September-2011-047.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Bidean nam Bian September, I find the first part of climbing a mountain is the hardest. I get out of breath very quickly, on this day there was a man with short arms climbing in front of us. I kept thinking how strong he was, he wasn&#8217;t even out of breath and here I was stopping for a rest constantly. I thought it was hard, which i like. There was a ledge sticking out which we climbed onto for photos. After reaching the top we decided while we were there it would be stupid not to climb up Stob Coire Sgreamhach. On the way down there is a kind of scramble drop, if that makes sense, we had to wait till a couple climbed up before we could go down. The lost Valley was like a place out of the Land that time forgot. I remember my knees were really hurting walking back to the car and the last bit felt like it was never going to end, that&#8217;s the worst my knees have felt. As we got back to the car there were bus loads of holiday makers getting ther photos taken with the Three Sisters behind them.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-052.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-045.JPG" alt="" /></p>

<p> Aonagh Eagach November, my all time favourite. Windy when we set off, coat on then off all the way to the top. Scrambling over the tops we only passed three people and saw a couple in the distance. A really hard scramble I thought and after climbing down the side of one part, I think Steven was trying to finish me off, a nearly fell off. Spinning round and looking down at a drop I thought this is it, then Steven climbed back down and pushed me back into the mountain. I was still stuck, it was slippy underfoot and i thought if i take my foot out of here I am still going to fall, the rock was really muddy and I remember saying my £160 coat is gonna be covered in muck, and my nose is running. What a stupid thing to think about, while my arms were wrapped round a rock, but as you can tell I made it back to the top. After having lunch we set off on the rest of the scramble. Darkness was setting in and we still had to decide which way to climb down, I wasn&#8217;t bothered whichever was the quickest, Steven decided we would try Clachaig gulley. &#8220;I can see the pub from here&#8221;, what a long way down. I was annoying Steven sliding, getting my feet stuck on rocks and him having to catch me and laughing at nothing in particular, &#8220;I can still see the pub from here&#8221;. I was getting bored and the end wasn&#8217;t getting any nearer, it felt like hours before we reached the bottom and it was dark. Hallelujah, nice pint of cider in the pub, before setting off and walking three miles with head torches in torrential rain and pitch blackness back to the car.</p>

<p> End of 2011 and start of 2012 on top of Killhope Law with Steven in the freezing cold with a small bottle of whisky, seeing in the New Year. My weekend binges in the local are no more, found two things I enjoy doing more 1) Spending time with Steven 2) Walking up Mountains.</p>

<p> Looking forward to this year, I am going to run the <a href="http://www.ratraceadventure.com/notorious/dsindex.html">Deerstalker</a> race in March in fancy dress which should be a laugh. I will be like a pig in mud, getting used to being dirty, makes a refreshing change from dresses and high heels.</p>

<p> My first wild camp in April on Skye, don&#8217;t know what to expect. I&#8217;ve only camped on a campsite with showers and lights. Told Steven I am taking my foundation and mascara which he says I dont need (but I do ), don&#8217;t want to scare the wildlife haha. Hopefully more climbing mountains and reaching a higher level than <a href="http://www.twitter.com/stevenhorner">Steven</a> and <a href="www.twitter.com/joncraddock">Jonathan</a> rock climbing ( thats a joke ). I will never be better than them. Followed by a summer holiday, somewhere hot with a small mountain in maybe ; ) of course there will be a mountain in it haha.</p>

<p> <em>Traci hasn&#8217;t got a blog of her own but you can follow her on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/traci_howarth">Twitter</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Focus, Fun and Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/18/focus-fun-and-learning/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-18T21:04:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/18/focus-fun-and-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not setting resolutions for 2012, the plan for the year can be summed up with:</p>

<blockquote><p>Focus, Fun and Learning</p></blockquote>

<p>Rather than blathering on, I am going to try to keep my posts short (lightweight) as much as possible this year. Sometime in the next couple of months you will see some changes on this site, but for now that&#8217;s all I&#8217;m saying.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>Planned trips/activities </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Scotland Winter Walking (February)</li>
<li>Run (March) - I have entered a short offroad race</li>
<li>Walking Skye (April)</li>
<li>Mountain Leader Training (May)</li>
<li>Relaxing Summer Holiday (June) - Maybe climb a mountain</li>
<li>UL Summer Summit (July/August)</li>
<li>Mountain Leader Assessment (September) - If enough experience</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Climbing</strong></p>

<p>Currently top roping indoors at around about 6b, intend to lead climb from February, then progress to rock outdoors in Spring/Summer.</p>

<p><strong>A few things I hope to learn more about:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Dry stone walling</li>
<li>Bushcraft &amp; wilderness skills</li>
<li>Geology Flora &amp; fauna</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Outdoor books on my 2012 reading list:</strong></p>

<p>*Disclaimer these are affiliate links</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0007424604/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0007424604">Ultimate Navigation Manual - Lyle Brotherton</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0007424604" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/071123180X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=071123180X">Granite and Grit: A Walker&#8217;s Guide to the Geology of British Mountains - Ronald Turnbull</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=071123180X" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0954151100/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0954151100">Hill Walking: The Official Handbook of the Mountain Leader and Walking Group Leader Schemes</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0954151100" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/095415116X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=095415116X">Rock Climbing: Essential Skills &amp; Techniques (Mountain Leader Training Handb) - Libby Peter</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=095415116X" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0715328425/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0715328425">The Complete Guide to Climbing and Mountaineering - Pete Hill</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0715328425" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0954151135/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0954151135">Winter Skills: Essential Walking and Climbing Techniques</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0954151135" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0723251754/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0723251754">The Wild Flower Key (Revised Edition) - Francis Rose</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0723251754" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0007236859/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0007236859">Collins Complete Guide - British Trees: A photographic guide to every common species</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0007236859" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1551051222/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1551051222">Bushcraft: Outdoor Skills and Wilderness Survival - Mors Kochanski</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=1551051222" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1905264941/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1905264941">The Natural Navigator - Tristan Gooley</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=1905264941" alt="" />
I would recommend watching Alan Titchmarshs - <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B0002XOZQU/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=B0002XOZQU%22>British%20Isles&lt;/a>&lt;img%20src=%22http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=B0002XOZQU&#8221;>British Isles: A Natural History</a> if you didn&#8217;t see it on the BBC in 2004, excellent in conjunction with Ronald Turnbulls <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/071123180X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=071123180X">Granite and Grit</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2011  - Where did it go?]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/11/2011-where-did-it-go/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-11T10:30:40+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/11/2011-where-did-it-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://stevenhorner.github.com/pics/Mamores%20July%202011%20001.JPG" alt="" /></p>

<p>I wrote a long post looking back at 2011, reviewing gear, trips and all sorts of stuff. I decided to bin it though and instead the main things to take from the year were the excellent trips with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/philoutdoors">Phil</a>, <a href="www.twitter.com/tramplite">Colin</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/tookiebunten">Tookie</a>, my dad &amp; of course <a href="http://www.twitter.com/traci_howarth">Traci</a>:</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1540">Cairngorms Everything but the kitchen sink</a></li>
<li>Cairngorms with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/philoutdoors">Phil</a>, <a href="www.twitter.com/tramplite">Colin</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.twitter.com/tookiebunten">Tookie</a> - <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1476">The Mamores </a></li>
<li>Ben Nevis via CMD</li>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1358">Ben Nevis in Winter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1568">Aonach Eagach</a></li>
<li>Bidean nam Bian</li>
</ul>


<p>All of those trips were with others, an exception to this would be my wander onto the <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1445">Black Cuillin</a> prior to the start of the <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1445">Highland ZigZag</a> which was stunning.</p>

<p>When it comes to gear, the most notable thing is the lack of it. During 2011 I barely bought any, yes I received a few free things to test before saying No to anymore. It can be hard not to spend your hard earned money on more gear, when everywhere you look you are being told how fantastic this, that or the other is but generally I resisted. Possibly the reason for this is my focus on my finances and my desire to become debt free, the key to this is <a href="http://www.youneedabudget.com/">YNAB</a> which I would highly recommend checking out.
<img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8143/7456924492_58237a8972_b.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2>What did I learn</h2>

<ul>
<li>I enjoy walking with others more than solo (which I do still enjoy).</li>
<li>I no longer want I.T. to be my main job and would like to work in the outdoors in some way.</li>
<li>I don&#8217;t need that new shiny kit.</li>
<li>Lightweight backpacking philosophy can be transfered to the rest of my life (less stuff).</li>
<li>Enjoy yourself no matter what!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The First Real Snow of the Winter]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/12/10/the-first-real-snow-of-the-winter/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-10T18:00:13+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/12/10/the-first-real-snow-of-the-winter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-040.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I had been planning a weekend wildcamping in the lake district but a dodgy shoulder led to a change of plans. Earlier in the week there was an inch of snow at home, sadly it has all melted now. My inbuilt Snowdar came into action today and after throwing a few things into my pack I was heading along the A689 West up Weardale.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Earlier in the week the entire top of the dale looked brilliant white, not so anymore but it was still white. The further up the dale I drove the more wintery things were looking. Once the fork towards Nenthead and Alston was taken it was another world and I had a big smile on my face. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-001.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-003.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I pulled into the car park at Killhope Wheel and was soon heading up through the tree stumps which is all that remains of the wood that was here until it was felled a few months ago. There was no sign of anyone else daft enough to be heading into the white cloud above. Once the the open access land was reached I headed directly towards the summit of Killhope law, using more tree stumps and a beck to handrail. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-007.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>When I say directly, it isn&#8217;t easy to walk directly over this terrain in the summer, nevermind when its covered in snow and every few feet you fall down a hole or over a tree stump. I didn&#8217;t take a map, I&#8217;ve walked this a few times and know the way. I did have the map on my phone and a compass. It would be fairly hard to get too lost up here for long if you have a compass, just head South and you will hit the main road to Nenthead, head East and hit the road to Allenheads eventually. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-011.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The trip to the summit was quicker than expected and as is now customary Kuksa summit pictures were taken.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-021.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-024.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I then headed towards what is called a shooters hut, it&#8217;s abandoned now, either that or they are particularly hard up. I stopped to take a few pictures of the impressive snow drifts before running a short distance down the track until a public right of way heads back over the ridge and around to where the Open Access land started. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Killhope-December-2011-043.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>As I descended back towards the road another set of footprints had walked a few hundred yards up the hill before turning around and heading back, shame they missed a nice walk. I loved this walk in the snow, not every trip needs to be an epic. This was only 3.5 miles.</p>

<iframe src="http://www.shareyouradventure.com/map/perma/3859/iframe" width="600" height="350"></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aonach Eagach & Two Potentially Dangerous Errors]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/12/09/aonach-eagach-two-potentially-dangerous-errors/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-09T18:39:08+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/12/09/aonach-eagach-two-potentially-dangerous-errors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-045.jpg" alt="" />
A couple of cheap hotel deals saw me driving towards Glencoe after breaking the journey North overnight at the Travelodge in Dumbarton. The forecast was far from encouraging, gusts in excess of 60mph and rain. Each time I drive through Glen Coe I dream of walking the Aonach Eagach and every time something happens to stop me. The previous trip I had managed to thwart the Cairngorm demons that did the same in the East of Scotland.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We were over an hour later than intended after snoozing the alarm one too many times. Recently I&#8217;ve stopped making any rigid plans and basically making it up when I get to a location. As I drove over Rannoch Moor and Buachaille Etive Mor came into view, it was to be option 1. The wind was lower than I expected and an option 2 jumped into my head, screaming to be done, this was the Aonach Eagach. The decision was made to drive to the foot of the track up to Am Bodach and check the conditions.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-006_1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The Aonach Eagach was clear of cloud, as were almost all the Munros in the area except for Bidean nam Bian. Things were looking good but the conditions at the top could be considerably different to the sheltered glen. We headed up the steep track towards Am Bodach, I agreed with Traci that we would make a decision once we reached the summit and then again at Meall Dearg.We weren&#8217;t going to take any chances on the ridge if the conditions didn&#8217;t look good.
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-038.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Strangely the higher we climbed the more the wind receded, by the time we made it to Meall Dearg, there was barely any wind. No clouds were heading our direction either, we had a window. The only thing I was slightly worried about was the daylight.
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-049.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>When walking alone it&#8217;s easy to judge my own pace even over difficult terrain but when walking with others it&#8217;s not so easy. Traci is fit and far from slow so we set off along the Aonach Eagach. We made good progress passing 3 people coming towards us, who didn&#8217;t look particularly happy.By about half way I made a comment that it was far easier than I was expecting. Yes there were drops down into the glen below and some climbs up and down but nothing that felt difficult or dangerous.</p>

<p>Maybe I spoke too soon. I waited for Traci and looked up at a longish climb upwards and said &#8220;this may get fun&#8221;, while I was waiting I noticed a very obvious path to my right which descended then joined a bit further along or so it appeared. This was error number 1. I led us around the right (North) side of the ridge. As we descended it became increasingly wet, mossy and slippy and we were descending more than I would of expected. I am not sure what went through my mind to take this route, it&#8217;s a ridge route why did I descend to one side. As we descended, the route became narrower and even wetter until there wasn&#8217;t really a route. I could still see what had looked like a path heading back up further along. But by now I would guess we were at a higher grade than scrambling, it felt like climbing. I was leading the way, then trying to help Traci place her feet and hands. We appeared to be almost at the bottom of &#8220;route&#8221; but there was a very steep, wet and slippy down climb onto a very narrow grassy ledge. I made it down without any problems but Traci is shorter and struggled and felt she was slipping. She lost her grip with her right hand and foot, swinging round while clinging on with her left hand. I can remember the moment perfectly, it was almost like everything slowed down around me. Luckily I was very close and pressed her back into the rock helping her find something to grip. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-055.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Traci like myself was strangely calm considering she could of very easily of fallen. For a few seconds I think Traci was slightly shook up (as you would expect) and didn&#8217;t want to move her hand . Yet less than a minute later she continued on as if nothing had happened. Most people would probably of frozen with fear and refused to move, clearly Traci is not most people. A few minutes later we were back on the ridge looking back at where we should of walked. I have no idea why I chose to go around the side or even if that really is a route. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-057.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-058.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-060.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The pinnacles that followed, one of which is the grade 2 I believe felt tame by comparison. Near the end of the ridge we could see four people heading for Sgorr nam Fiannaidh, we weren&#8217;t far behind them but couldn&#8217;t see them when we reached the summit. That was the Aonach Eagach over but everyone knows it&#8217;s the descent when most accidents happen and we couldn&#8217;t relax yet the Clachaig is still some distance away. <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-068.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I had read ages ago about the gulley down to the Clachaig, several people had different opinions on it. Some saying it&#8217;s dangerous and should be avoided (deaths have happened), while others think there is nothing wrong with it. I decided to take a look at it, if it looked too steep or difficult we would head back up and head further long and descend via the col before the Pap of Glencoe. The path is cairned and well marked higher up and we decided we would descend the gulley (the path next to the gulley). This was a mistake (error number 2), it wasn&#8217;t particularly difficult or in the dry weather, very slippery. It was just very slow going, Traci was becoming tired and decided it a good idea to slide at one point down some rock.
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-076.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;m not sure it would be an exageration to say it took as long to descend the gulley to the Clachaig, as it did to cross the Aonach Eagach. We were beginning to think the pub was a mirage. We reached the grass and the road at the bottom just as the last of the of the light went. Descending in darkness would of been dangerous.</p>

<p>We still had the walk along the road to the car in the dark but we had earned a pint and a rest. Reluctantly we left the main hotel bar, the climbers bar was closed for refurbishments. It was now drizzling, waterproofs were slipped into and head torches worn. The route march back to the car passed happily uneventfully.</p>

<p>We had slightly more of an adventure than I had intended, lessons were learned but I still have no idea why I didn&#8217;t stick to the ridge. I have a GPX file of our tracks, but it&#8217;s hard to read on the map. The 1:10k maps which don&#8217;t have contours may help to identify exactly where I made a detour.</p>

<p>I will be returning at least once next year in the summer to walk the ridge correctly, possibly in the winter too.</p>

<iframe src="http://www.shareyouradventure.com/map/perma/3857/iframe" width="600" height="350"></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cairngorms - Everything but the kitchen sink]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/12/03/cairngorms-everything-but-the-kitchen-sink/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-03T22:22:59+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/12/03/cairngorms-everything-but-the-kitchen-sink</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-040.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Day 1 = 1 mile <br>
Day 2 = 16 miles <br>
Day 3 = 22 miles <br>
Total = 39 miles <br>
Munros = 2</p>

<p>Last year it seamed every other week I was out walking with Phil Turner, both of us have been so busy this year that the trips have been few and few far between until recently. Remarkably I emailed a date when I was free and the stars must of aligned and Phil was also free. A couple of weeks later and I arrived at Turner Towers to see him watching a live video of @pilgrimchris walking through the woods and responding to messages Phil was typing to him. This was a demonstration of Bambuser, impressive if you have a decent signal (I rarely do where I walk).
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111112_081712.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The original plan had been to walk an EPIC Cairngorms Colin Ibbotson route, but we needed nice weather to do it justice. The forecast was for very strong winds and low cloud, a change of plan was needed. On route North we decided to head towards Braemar and the Linn of Dee. I had never driven to Braemar before, the road is a bit of a nightmare and I&#8217;ve no idea how they ever get any skiing surely the road is permanenty shut. Eventually we arrived at the Linn of Dee around 3pm (£2 parking). The plan which had evolved on the way was to camp in some trees a mile from the car, it was beginning to get dark and windy. Camping in trees in the wind, probably isn&#8217;t the best idea (we survived). The spot was perfect, sheltered, flat and close to the the river, a few minutes after arriving I had the Trailstar pitched and Phil had his Gossamer Gear Tarp up. It was starting to get dark and it wasn&#8217;t long before food was eaten and we retired to our shelters.</p>

<p>This time of year, the nights are long, very long. Eventually after listening to a few Podcasts I dozed off and after what seamed like a week I woke expecting it to be 6am, only to find it was 1am. What do you do when you find yourself wide awake wild camping with several hours spare. Unfortunately for me I had forgotten to bring my Kindle, I tried reading on my phone but after it slipped out my hand a few times hitting me in the face I gave up on that. I listened to music for a while, but got bored of that too (I really need to update my Spotify playlists). Eventually I gave up with digital distractions and listened to the wind and the river, my thoughts drifted to plans for the future and lots of different ideas. At some point I nodded off and woke a few hours later and waited for the sound of movement from Phil, luckily it wasn&#8217;t too long.</p>

<p>After our breakfasts we had a quick discussion and decided to stay low for the day, due to the MWIS forecast for gales again. This included the classic TGO Challenge FWA route through Glen Feshie which lots of people rave about. The majority of the days walking until we reached Glen Feshie is quite barren and not the sort of terrain I normally enjoy, the North Pennines and North York Moors are on my doorstep and maybe this familiarity with bleak landscapes shape my regular desire for &#8220;pointy bits&#8221;. Possibly it&#8217;s the reading list I have or the walking companions but I am now noticing far more than in the past. Rather than rushing from point to point, walks certainly feel more like a journey with discoveries on route. Actually walking with the map in hand and constantly picking things out as you pass helps with this, previously I tended to just check my position on an O.S. map on my phone at regular intervals but the smaller area shown doesn&#8217;t allow you to spot things in the distance. I always carry a map but often never look at it other than in camp or at a food stop. Making the route up as we walked added something to this trip.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-008.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> White Bridge (presumably it was once white?) was passed a couple of miles after setting off. We then headed for Red House with its warning signs. It has a nice little platform bodged together if you fancy sleeping here. The building looked fairly sound if a little drafty with no door but I have no door on the Trailstar.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-009.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Our route then followed Geldie Burn and the continuation of the very obvious track, my map reading skills weren&#8217;t exactly needed yet. We stopped for tensies (like elevensies but earlier, a food stop) opposite the ruins of Geldie Lodge where the track becomes a bit narrower and shortly after boggier. The next section from Geldie Lodge to Eidart Bridge is a bit moist in places but with some pacer pole olympic jumps most can be avoided. Eidart bridge isn&#8217;t the nicest looking bridge it looks like some scaffolding across the river but the falls beneath are beautiful and could make for some nice photos on a less grey day. The target for dinner (lunch to those strange Southerners) was what Phil described as a horse hut, where he had seen wild horses previously. Horses with a hut don&#8217;t sound very wild to me but I decided not to question him about it. The &#8220;hut&#8221; was of the wild camping variety, it had 1.5 walls and a roof. I&#8217;ve noticed even after 2 years of knowing Phil he is still easily pleased with Horner and corner references. He took great delight in taking a picture of me eating my dinner in the corner of the 1.5 walled &#8220;hut&#8221;.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-024.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> We started to see trees lining the water side as we entered Glen Feshie and we were greeted by several deer, unfortunately they didn&#8217;t look too magnificent due to only their guts remaining at the side of the track. They looked quite fresh, presumably shot and gutted recently. I was beginning to wonder why people liked Glen Feshie so much, but the further we walked the more I understood. The area just South of Ruigh Aiteachain looked stunning as the sun started to dip behind the hills and a wide open area presented itself.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-025.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Ruigh Aiteachain bothy is a 2 roomed building with sleeping platform/bunks in one room and the fire in the other. I have visited several bothy but have never slept in any. Phil wasn&#8217;t too thrilled when I mentioned this, he muttered something about mice and it being a busy bothy not far from a road. He then rushed out to try the &#8220;luxury&#8221; toilet. The &#8220;luxury&#8221; toilet is a drain with a kermode above, you have to collect a bucket of water first from above. You really wouldn&#8217;t want to be in a rush, best not to eat too many Mountain House meals.</p>

<p> Shelters were again pitched, this time about 100 yards from the bothy. We had walked all day and not seen a single person. There was evidence that people were staying in the bothy that night, several carrier bags of food and gear hanging up. Probably another reason Phil ran from the building, the people not the food. As the sun retreated further and the darkness began to take hold, a couple of people appeared at the bothy. They hung around outside for quite a while before disappearing inside, while we sat leaning against trees reading. Shortly after we retreated to our own domains where I dozed listening to music. Just before 7pm I saw a headtorch approaching the bothy quickly. Soon after I began to hear loud noises inbetween the songs I was listening to. I realised it wasn&#8217;t Phil having a party under his tarp, someone in the bothy was playing a guitar. I think the guitar playing went on for ages, I am pleased we didn&#8217;t sleep in there.</p>

<p> Again I woke up in the early hours, this time thinking someone had turned a spotlight on or the bothy dwellers had decided to add a light show to accompany the guitar. Once the sleep was rubbed from my eyes, the spotlight was revealed as the moon. The next hour was spent watching stars in the clear sky, at some point sleep returned and I woke at 4am and made some coffee. 2 hours until the agreed wakeup time, lost in my own thoughts the time disappeared surprisingly quickly.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-032.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> The only problem with the route we had chosen was that the only obvious options open to us was either crossing over the mountains or returning the way we had came. We both wanted to gain some height, we left the overnight spot in the early morning darkness and easily found the vehicle track heading up next to Allt Choire Chaoil. As the height was gained, the wind increased, an inviting path to our left lead to a small hill (sub 900m). I continued on after a few glances from Phil. I hate tracks that you can see for what seams like miles, this was one of those. Views of Meall Dubhag distracted my attention from the wind and the track.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-049.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Once above 900m the area became relatively flat but here the plateau is covered with peat hags, unlike the rocky plateau around Ben Macdui. On this occassion we were pleased of the shooters track, avoiding lots of boggy messiness. We stopped for food as the track crossed Coachan Dubh, at this point Phil realised the mice he had complained about inhabiting bothies had taken their revenge. While he was sleeping they had helped themselves to his Kit Kat, he still ate the remains (of the Kit Kat not the mice).
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-047.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-057.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> So far we were lucky and been afforded good visibility. This being the Cairngorms when we set off from our stop in a slight dip, the cloud had started to descend. We headed to Tom Dubh (most obvious feature) now that the track was coming to an end. The visibility was now down to around 15-20m or was that feet I can&#8217;t remember now. I&#8217;m sure Phil had a grin, he was going to get a chance to practise his navigation. I&#8217;d been reading Ultimate Navigation and improving mine but enjoyed watching someone else navigate (probably still be there if I did the navigating). A bearing was taken and we followed it to a stream (whatever they call them in Scotland), the followed it up to the ridge.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-059.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> There was no way I was missing out Munros when we were this close and I was pleasantly surprised when Phil agreed. We couldn&#8217;t see anything on the ridge and the path up to Sgor an Lochain Uaine (Angels Peak) went upwards into the cloud forever. When I know I&#8217;m not far from from a summit I always forget any tiredness and speed up (unless walking with Colin and he almost runs by me). Sadly there was absolutely no view from the summit, but of course the summit Kuksa pictures were taken anyway.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-068.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111113_125513.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> The next summit along the ridge was Cairn Toul, I&#8217;m sure there was a comment made about maybe taking a path around it if there was one (bet Phil is pleased he didn&#8217;t). We descended in the cloud over rocky ground before the path started to ascend again, the cloud started to thin slightly and we were lucky enough to see a Brocken Spectre again (second time this year). The route up to the summit of Cairn Toul cleared as Phil squirted Peanut butter into his mouth from a Tomato sauce bottle. The realisation that we were about to see an inversion was all the fuel I needed as I raced for the summit.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111113_131438.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> At the summit shelter we were indeed presented with an inversion, intially only the highest peaks were poking out from the cloud. The cloud continued to descend revealing ever more mountains. I have no idea how long we stood there in awe of the view, taking pictures and identifying mountains. I had forgotten to charge my camera, luckily the phone didn&#8217;t do a bad job when the camera eventually gave up. We could see Lochnagar briefly before the cloud reclaimed it. I would guess we were at the summit for an hour, it then started to dawn on us that we had a long walk back to the car. We reluctantly started the descent, then reascent up Stob Boire an t-Saighdeir before once again descending to the path down Coire Odhar and Corrour bothy. We didn&#8217;t have the time to bag Bod an Deamhain (The Devil&#8217;s Point), which was still shrouded in cloud until we reached Corrour anyway.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-November-2011-080.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111113_133830.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111113_140106.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> There was no time to hang about at Corrour either, we checked if it was occupied, it wasn&#8217;t. We had been talking about sharing my spare dehydrated meal at the bothy but we knew we would lose light rapidly soon. We decided to head down Glen Dee to White Bridge then back to the Linn of Dee where my car awaited. The path is very faint (or not where the O.S. say it is) and boggy where it splits near Corrour (we missed it). We managed to join the path and continued our boggy journey at pace, as the light faded. Initially in the darkness I wore an e+Lite but it wasn&#8217;t up to the job over the uneven bog and was swapped for a Tikka Plus.</p>

<p> I would guess we walked for at least an hour in the darkness before reaching White Bridge, and a good track to follow. It was a relief to finally be on an easy track with less than an hour to the end, behind us at White Bridge was a bright light aproaching faster than we were walking. Eventually we realised it wasn&#8217;t a vehicle but a man on a bike with headtorch and bike lights. By now we were tired and both dreaming of the fish and chips in Braemar, the thought spurred us on.</p>

<p> We arrived to an empty car park, except for 1 Landrover driving by. In the previous 2 days we had seen no one except for a couple of people at the bothy and the man on his bike. There were many, many more stand out moments on this trip. This is long enough without describing ptarmagins, snow buntings, horses, etc.</p>

<p> Day 3 felt like 22 miles, especially when it included two 4000 foot peaks with short daylight hours. In hindsight I wonder if walking via Derry Lodge, instead of Glen Dee would of been the better option.</p>

<p> We were denied those fish and chips in Braemar, it was shut along with almost every other eatery we passed. The MacDonalds at Perth tasted fantastic, which shows how hungry we must of been. I don&#8217;t think myself and Phil ever do boring trips when we walk together.</p>

<p> <iframe src="http://www.shareyouradventure.com/map/perma/3226/iframe" width="600" height="350"></iframe></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wanderer Returns]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/11/24/wanderer-returns/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-24T14:00:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/11/24/wanderer-returns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-September-2011-049.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Sometimes it can be good to take a break from things and reflect on life and check that the path you are on, is the one you really want to follow. The break on this site has been part of that process.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Several months ago I decided I would no longer review Outdoor gear, unless I had bought it with my own money. Shortly after this the whole bloggers reviewing gear conversation blew up on various sites. I commented on one site, but generally decided to keep out of the conversation and wait until things calmed down. My personal opinion is that you can do what you like, it&#8217;s your site, but personally I would rather disclose if I was given something. The reason for stopping reviewing is nothing to do with the online discussion, it&#8217;s purely personal. Reviewing gear isn&#8217;t something that I enjoy and trying to think of something interesting to write feels far too much of a chore (the day job is enough work). That&#8217;s not why I spend my time in the outdoors and in the online outdoor community. Having said that, I love to read about gear and find out what others think of it.</p>

<p>In the last week alone I have turned down 3 companies offering gear to review, several people thought I was nuts for saying No.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scarborough-10K.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>While the site may of been quiet, away from the online world, my life has been anything but sedentary. After an operation on my heart I decided to start running regularly again and entered an race for the first time in years. The <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=scarborough%2010k&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CDoQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.yorkshirecoast10k.co.uk%2F&amp;ei=xz3OTumOFobe8QPMloTGDw&amp;usg=AFQjCNGiDnstSHTWOhh7qznBWGAl7VGa4Q">Scarborough 10K</a> which somehow I persuaded Traci (Girlfriend) to enter and we successfully completed the course. I may not of been happy at my time but the main thing is that my heart appears to be fixed and I will now need to find another excuse for being rubbish.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111023_165854-600x450.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A couple of years ago I started bouldering at <a href="www.durhamclimbingcentre.co.uk/">Durham Climbing Centre</a>, but the stop start nature of it caused problems with the ticker. Now that everything is OK, I have been climbing at <a href="www.sunderlandwall.co.uk/">Sunderland Wall</a> for the last few months with <a href="http://jonathancraddock.com">Jonathan Craddock</a> and more recently <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/traci_howarth">Traci</a> too. I&#8217;m still not very good, but have managed to climb up to F6b+ top roping. The next stage is to learn Lead climbing, then progress to rock outdoors next year.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111113_131438.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> There hasn&#8217;t been a lack of walking either, a couple of trips with <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/philoutdoors">Phil Turner</a> most recently an Epic couple of days in the Cairngorms which delighted us with inversions, Broken Spectres, 4000 feet summits and night walking. An earlier trip also included <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/tramplite">Colin Ibbotson</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/tookiebunten">Tookie Bunten</a> in the Cairngorms and a trio of Trailstars.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-September-2011-073.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-045.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Somehow I have been fortunate enough to find someone who is nuts as me (<a href="http://twitter.com/#!/traci_howarth">Traci</a>) and is happy (so she says) to wander up mountains, climb walls, run and generally put up with me talking about the outdoors. Over the last few months I&#8217;ve dragged Traci up several mountains including Bidean nam Bian, Ben Nevis, Scafell Pike, Helvellyn, boggy hills in Weardale and last weekend across the Aonach Eagach. Before meeting me she&#8217;d never done anything like this.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-September-2011-047.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Walking with others is something I really enjoy, while I love solitude at times too. It is a very different experience walking with more than just my Kuksa for company. The majority of memorable trips have been shared experiences. Over the years I have encouraged and taken walking many friends, often their first experience of walking and the outdoors. I love doing this and a natural progression is to work towards the <a href="http://www.mltuk.org/">Mountain Leader qualification</a> which I have now embarked on. Hopefully I will attend the training course in May next year, I have far more than the required 20 &#8220;Quality&#8221; mountain days needed. Several months later I will then need to pass the Assessment and then will be a Summer Mountain Leader (fingers crossed). I have a plan in place which will hopefully take me to where I want to be in a couple of years and for the first time, what I&#8217;m doing and where I&#8217;m going feels like the correct path.</p>

<p> So what is going to happen to this site? <br>
 Now that I have formally announced no more reviews I can focus on the things I enjoy again, writing about my experiences, skills learned and observations. I mentioned above that I have a plan for the next couple of years, so much so that I have almost all my holiday scheduled until March 2013. This includes the <a href="http://ultralightsummit.com/2011/10/31/the-polls-are-closed/">Ultralight Backpackers Summit</a> <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com">Hendrik Morkel</a> is organising in Slovenia next year (dates to be confirmed). These trips and my experiences <strong>will</strong> now be more regularly written up on here.</p>

<p> I have 2 other Outdoor related sites in the pipeline, both involve a lot of work but once there is something to show I will write about it here. Thanks to everyone I have walked with and spoken to online. I have returned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Water]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/09/11/water/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-11T16:15:20+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/09/11/water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Ullswater-Doris-049.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Water the single most important thing to us humans. You could get away without shelter or food for several days or weeks but not so for water. Supposedly we can last 3 days without water, but long before that you would experience headaches, probably dizziness and obviously a total lack of energy. Even though it&#8217;s so important many of us backpackers don&#8217;t give it much thought or we just do what we&#8217;ve always done.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I like the idea that each time you go on a trip you should try something new and I have experimented over the last year or two trying to gauge how much water to carry depending on the environment and the expected weather conditions. Below is a shortened summary showing how my usage has changed (top oldest).</p>

<p><strong>Day Walks </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>1L Flask of tea &amp; 500ml orange juice</li>
<li>2 x 500ml water bottle</li>
<li>1 x 500ml water bottle &amp; Kuksa</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Overnighter </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>2L Camelbak, Sigg bottle &amp; 1lLPlatypus for camp</li>
<li>2 x 500ml water bottle &amp; 1L Platypus for camp</li>
<li>1 x 500ml water bottle, Kuksa &amp; 1L Platypus for camp</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_123407.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>There can be huge differences in the volume of water needed for a trip, I&#8217;ve had several trips where I have got it wrong, going back several years. One that comes to mind was walking the Wainwrights around Ennerdale, after a wildcamp on Haystacks I filled the 2L Camelbak and the 500ml <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Sigg_Traveller_60cl_Water_Bottle_271-1753.html">SIG bottle</a> before setting off. The day turned out to be hot and back in 2007 I was carrying a lot more in my pack than today, after walking over Brandreth, Green Gable, Great Gable, Kirk Fell, Pillar, Scoat Fell, Steeple and Haycock I had run out of water and hadn&#8217;t realised how low the water level had become due to the Camelbak being hidden in the pack. There was no water up high and I was feeling the effects, very sluggish, headaches and I just wanted to sit down. On this occassion I checked the map and made a detour to Silver cove and found a stream thankfully bubbling away. I was in the lake district beneath me was Ennerdale which I obviously could of headed for. I had an added problem on this trip, this was probably the first occassion when I began to notice I had a heart problem and just wanted to lie down and sleep, the water problem just made it worse.</p>

<p>I had other occassions when I ran out of water on day walks due to not knowing how much water was remaining in the camelbak. On one of these the pipes froze in winter, you can get insulated pipes which the person I was walking with had, theirs froze too. This was the end of using reservoirs hidden in my pack. Something that could be worth a look is the new <a href="http://www.camelbak.com/Sports-Recreation/Accessories/Flowmeter.aspx">flow meter</a> from Camelbak which has a display that lets you know how much water is remaining among other information. I find looking at a clear bottle much simpler and cheaper. I find turning a water bottle upside down in winter prevents the opening freezing, water freezes from the top down.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Fullscreen-capture-11092011-132336.bmp.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> I have never treated water with any form of filter, tablet or any other method. This is likely due to the areas I choose to walk being mountainous and/or remote. Although I have walked with people who spent 10 minutes filtering water through an inline filter while I stood there scooping water with my Kuksa and drinking it. This was a from a fast moving stream in the North York Moors. Some may think I am stupid but I try to choose a source of water that hopefully wouldn&#8217;t be contaminated, I have never been ill. If I walked through more urban areas or lots of flat farmed areas I may think differently.</p>

<p> This is my personal choice, I&#8217;ve seen many walkers carry 5+ litres of water in the Lake District or Scotland and never need to stop to fill up. They generally do need to stop due to carrying 5+kg of water weight on their backs though. I mentioned earlier its the skill of judging what water maybe available, clearly if you are walking in hot dry areas or polluted ares of the world you will NEED to carry much more water.</p>

<p> Two of my favourite pieces of kit are my Kuksa and Platypus, the Kuksa I bought while on a trip to Finland and was introdused to them by <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com">Hendrik Morkel</a>. Since then it is attached to my pack on every trip I make. It&#8217;s not just used for taking pictures on summits, it&#8217;s main use is to scoop water whenever I pass a stream. You could use a far lighter plastic cup but it&#8217;s just not the same as a carved wooden kuksa. The 1L platypus is one of those bits of kit that is just so simple you give it no thought. It rolls up to nothing and sits in the very top of my pack waiting until the last water point of the day where I will fill it up for my camp water.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_121908.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> I&#8217;ve used the same platypus for the last 4-5 years and it has never leaked or developed any problems. <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/">Webtogs</a> asked if I wanted to test a hydration system a couple of months ago, I already had this post in mind so asked for another <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus/">Playtpus</a>. I could of chosen a more expensive <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Camelbak/">Camelbak</a> but I prefer the simple system I&#8217;ve developed. I received the <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser </a>which features a pipe so you can hide the bladder in your pack and drink using the bite valve without having to do a strange yoga stretching position to remove a bottle from your pack side pockets. The bite valve isn&#8217;t as nice as Camelbaks but it works, having said Camelbaks are better I dislike the newer style shut off valve on Camelbaks. Their old valve was far easier to operate one handed. The <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a> doesn&#8217;t feature a shut valve, this could be a problem as the bite valve becomes old and water seeps out but I haven&#8217;t used it for long enough. An <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Shutoff_Valve_101435.html">upgraded valve</a> is available as an upgrade.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Skitched-image0-600x438.png" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_154924.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> The <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a> features a very simple clip that allows you to attach the pipe to your pack or clothes, I would remove it though as its a bit unnescessary most packs have loops you can easily push the bite valve into rather than using the extra metal clip.</p>

<p> I already mentioned that I decided I no longer want to use a water reservoir with pipes, be it a camelbak or a <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a> due to finding it hard to track how much water I was drinking and how much is remaining. So why ask for a <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Hoser</a>, I wanted the main reservoir not the pipe and may on future trips abroad use an inline filter to fill up my other water containers. The Platypus has changed slightly since I bought my original years ago. The new ones are made of slightly less rigid plastic, have a loop to either hang or pick it up by and the entry/exit to the platypus is now on the corner. Having the entry/exit on the corner makes sense if you are using it in a hydration system, all the water will be funneled towards the pipe due the shape of the reservoir. Camelbak pipes exit near the centre at the bottom and the last bit of water can be hard to suck through. Camelbaks also have seperate fill up/pipe exits giving 2 possible points of failure rather than the 1 on the Platypus.</p>

<p> The only criticism I would have of the Platypus is they can take considerably longer to fill due to the small simple top. The Hoser doesn&#8217;t come with a standard cap like my old one, because it is intended to be used with the pipe and bite valve. Most bottle tops from fizzy drinks containers do fit though or you could buy some <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Closure_Cap__pack_of_two__101432.html">official closure caps</a> from Platypus. As well as a criticism, it is also an advantage, keeping it incredibly simple is one less thing to go wrong. Several times I&#8217;ve struggled to remove the large opening cap from Camelbaks when they have stuck, almost breaking my thumbs to open them, slight exageration but it hurt. Platypus may of already of answered this with their Big Zip but Keep It Simple Stupid (Kiss) comes to mind with less to go wrong and leak I will stick to my current system.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20110911_155016.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> So to summarise my water system for walking in the British mountains: I always carry my Kuksa to drink whenever I pass a stream or other water source, 1 or 2 500ml clear water bottles and a <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">1L Platypus</a> minus the hose/pipe for camp at night or for when water maybe scarce at higher levels during the day. This isn&#8217;t really a review of the Platypus there&#8217;s not much to review and the best recommendation is I asked for another over several other more expensive fancy systems.</p>

<p> <strong>Gear Mentioned</strong></p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Hoser_1_Litre_100712.html">Platypus 1L Hoser</a> = £15.99 (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Sigg_Traveller_60cl_Water_Bottle_271-1753.html">Sigg 60cl Traveller</a> = £14.99 (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Closure_Cap__pack_of_two__101432.html">Platypus Closure Caps x2</a> = £3.99 (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Platypus_Shutoff_Valve_101435.html">Platypus Shutoff Valve</a> = (Webtogs)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/products/catalog?q=camelbak+antidote&amp;hl=en&amp;prmd=ivns&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.&amp;biw=1280&amp;bih=909&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;tbm=shop&amp;cid=4745813139539568444&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=RsFsTp_KFYbm-gaexoz2BA&amp;ved=0CF8Q8wIwAQ">Camelbank Reservoir</a> - £21 (Best Price)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/products/catalog?q=camelbak+flow+meter&amp;hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;tbm=shop&amp;cid=6445640845516168167&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hcFsTvK3OtCN-wabnbXvBA&amp;ved=0CFMQ8wIwAA">Camelbak Flow Meter</a> = £16 (Best Price)</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/search?q=kuksa&amp;hl=en&amp;tbm=shop&amp;aq=f">Kuksa</a> = £22 (Best price) 500ml water bottle = Free use one someone is throwing out</li>
</ul>


<p> I would be interested in other peoples water systems and what they use, please let me know in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Mamores]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/07/29/the-mamores/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-29T15:18:24+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/07/29/the-mamores</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-059.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The Mamores, if you haven&#8217;t heard of them you are missing out on some of the finest mountains in Britain. If you&#8217;ve been lucky enough to walk up Ben Nevis on a clear day you will have noticed them to the South, the opposite side of Glen Nevis. These have been on my ever increasing To Do list for years. Last year I walked 4 of the 10 Munros that make up the Mamores as part of the <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=998">Ring of Steall</a>, sadly the tops were in cloud almost all day but it was still a fabulous walk. I then tried to walk them in March on my <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1338">Shearing trip</a> but had to change plans due to their high avalanche risk. In May they were included in my <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1393">Highland ZigZag</a> route which I ended very early. Fast forward 2 months&#8230;</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://www.lightweightoutdoors.com/">Phil Turner</a> contacted me about doing some pointy bits together, we hadn&#8217;t had a trip since the <a href="http://lightweightoutdoors.com/?p=1959">Three Beinns</a> route in March on Arran. Our trips are always memorable for one reason or another and I very rarely pass on the opportunity to walk together. Phil was going to be walking Ben Nevis helping the Deaf and Blind Michael to the summit and suggested walking in the area the following day. The Mamores jumped into my head, before I got chance to reply Phil suggested <a href="http://www.stevenfallon.co.uk/">Steve Fallons</a> route over them. Great minds think alike (not sure we fit in that category).</p>

<p>A few messages later and the details were arranged along with <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/tramplite">Colin Ibbotson</a> walking with us too, a training session before his Colorado Trail trip 2 weeks later. Finally I was going to meet Colin, although I was slightly worried about trailing in his dust as he floated over the mountains with ease.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-008.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A couple of weeks later I was at the start of the route with Colin being eaten by midge while we waited for Phil. He was 40 minutes late but we let him off, he had spent 18 hours the day before on the previously mentioned DeafBlind Ben Nevis trip. Another 15 minutes later after Phil had packed his <a href="http://www.tramplite.com/">Tramplite</a> pack Colin was loaning him, we were finally heading up out of the glen through the trees. Once out of the trees there was a steep climb up onto the ridge (if it could be called a ridge), before this though we needed some water and Phil sent Colin down to the Allt a&#8217; Choire Dheirg to fill all our Platypus, he was in training after all. More likely Phil and I could probably do with the rest before tackling the steep ascent ahead.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-009.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The ascent was easier than expected, gaining height rapidy and soon reaching the ridge leading up to Mullach nan Coirean and being presented with breath taking views in every direction. The weather was excellent, although a breeze would of been welcome. Cloud was covering several of the higher peaks like Ben Nevis and Aonach Mor but this just added a little drama to the view. I almost forgot the obligatory Kuksa Munro summit shot, luckily Phil reminded me. Mullach nan Coirean done, only 9 more Munros to go.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-013.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-024.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The next target Stob Ban was easier than expected, maybe due to the views or possibly because we were busy talking. We had been taking it quite easy, Colin was being kind and slowing for us along with sitting admiring the view and enjoying the weather on each summit. It was now after 4pm, having not set off until 12. We could see a perfect wildcamping spot with running water from Lochan Coire nam Miseach, it was agreed we would wildcamp for the night. A shorter day than I was expecting.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-034.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Shelters were soon setup my <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1003">Trailstar</a>, Vango Helium 200? (Phil) and <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=21&amp;products_id=175">Solo Trailstar</a> (Colin). After a few hours admiring the view, talking, cooking and feeding the midge we disappeared to our own shelters for the night with assurances from Phil that he would be awake by 6.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-040.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> The following morning I had proof that miracles really do happen, I heard Phil moving about just before 6am. I&#8217;d been awake for a couple of hours contemplating, what exactly I can no longer remember. By 7 we were heading up to just beneath Sgurr an Iubhair and along the Devils Ridge. The views were even better than the day before with clearer skies, except for Ben Nevis and the Aonachs which were crowned with cloud. It was already sweltering or maybe it was just the exersion from ascending to the ridge. This was my second time on the Devils Ridge which conjures up images of deathly drops and clinging on by the fingernails. Yet in reality its very tame, there is one very short section that could add some scrambling fun but we bypassed this on the way to Sgurr a&#8217; Mhaim. The last pull up to the summit stuck in my mind that it went on forever and was expecting a false summit but happily I was wrong. I was last up there while on the Ring of Steall and couldn&#8217;t see anything for cloud, today the views were breath taking or was that due to chasing after Colin.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-051.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> I started to cross the scrambly section on our return while the others went around again but there&#8217;s one slightly more difficult section, nothing too difficult, but I decided rather than making the others wait while I put away my poles that I would retreat and follow them instead. The ridge looks more impressive with your back to Sgurr a&#8217; Mhaim. As we walked back along the Devils Ridge we were treated to a rare sight, a Broken Specktre (none of us had seen one before). We eventually returned to where we had joined the ridge earlier and could see our campsite of less than 2 hours earlier.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-055.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> The next target was Sgurr an Iubhair which felt like quite a pull up to its summit at 3284 feet from the top there are once again fabuous views in every direction. This has been promoted to Munro status in 1984 and then subsequently stripped of it again. Colin declared that it was a Munro in his eyes, its certainly high enough and feels like one. So its now an Ibbotson Munro, we maybe should of planted a flag!</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-064.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> The next pointy bit on the route is Am Bodach which stuck in my mind last time as having a very steep ascent when I walked it in reverse, so a steep descent this time, I don&#8217;t mean I walked backwards. The ascent this time was much easier gradually rising to a quite large flat summit with views that just keep getting better the further we walk. The 3 of us sat on the top trying to name as many mountains as we could and looking them up on the map. Certain mountains stand out and yes we could see Schiehallion 35 miles away, as well as much closer mountains and ridges like the Aonach Eagach, yet what stood out the most was Sgorr Dhearg and Sgorr Dhonuill not mountains that any of us were familiar with. We spent 30 minutes at the summit enjoying lazing in the sun, eating and taking Kuksa summit shots.</p>

<p> The descent from Am Bodach in these conditions was a little disappointing after I had been declaring how steep it was to Colin and Phil. The last time I walked it I could only see a short distance in front of me, thats my excuse. What did become quite apparant on this trip is how much fast I descend compared to others. The same can be said of Colin when ascending, he motors by everyone even when he is taking it easy, while Phil and myself were usually weezing trying to catch our breath with racing hearts.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-079.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> I am not sure why buy I can&#8217;t remember much of Stob Coire a&#8217; Chairn either on this trip or on my previous ascent. It could be that the eye is drawn to An Gearanach and An Garbhanach or back to Sgurr a&#8217; Mhaim. Possibly there could be some sort of memory erasing device located at the summit, which could explain how the day disappeared so fast. I can remember reaching the Bealach a&#8217; Chadha Riabhaich where we left our bags before climbing up the rocky fun route up to the Munro of An Gearanach, although An Garbhanach which you cross on the way is the better mountain. Without our bags which were actually very ligthweight, we almost floated to the top or was that due to the Mountain House Flatulence. Up until this point we had seen no one, suddenly just after one of us noted the fact lots of people appeared out of nowhere. We didn&#8217;t hang around for long, quickly turning tail and heading back to our packs.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-092.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Rather than reascending Stob Coire a&#8217; Chairn we headed down to fill up on water and contoured around the side over boggy ground rejoining the path and heading up towards Na Gruagaichean, although there is a &#8220;sharp gap&#8221; as described by Steve Fallon. The gap was quite easy, I decided to get a head start on Colin and descended the gap quickly and rather than waiting for the others to catch up. I headed straight up towards the summit, but I could feel Colin chasing me down. On reaching the top we met a guy who has walked up from Kinlochleven and after a couple of minutes discussion Phil reached the top and mentioned that a woman was passing him on the way down, she fell head first, stuck her arm out which Phil grabbed and somehow swung her around landing on her feet. Sounds like she was lucky.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-094.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> By now Phil and myself were beginning to tire, I&#8217;m not as fit as I used to be and Phil isn&#8217;t used to Pointy bits. There was a discussion regarding myself and Phil just walking up to Binnein Mor and then heading back down. Colin wanted to walk the extra 2 Munros. Once again we jettisoned out packs and stored them this time a lot higher at 3400 feet before climbing to the summit of Binnein Mor which is at 3707ft is the highest of the Mamores. Kuksa pictures were quickly taken before rushing back to our packs, considerably more slowly than the start of the day. Phil and myself had made the decision to miss the last 2 Munros, I just felt drained my legs and feet weren&#8217;t complaining just a general lack of energy. Colin was determined to walk the last 2 Munros, we agreed to meet him at the small loch beneath Binnein Beag after Sgurr Eilde Mor. We lay on the gassy bank with our packs as we watched Colin race off with far more energy than is human after a long very hot day in the mountains.</p>

<p> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-096.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Once Colin disappeared from view we followed the route down to Coire a&#8217; Bhinnein where several kuksas of water were consumed as we watched Colin almost sprinting to the the summit of Sgurr Eilde Mor. It was clear now how much Colin must of been holding back for us, either that or he could almost taste the food we were planning to eat at the end. Pressing on to the redezvous point at the small loch, Phil and myself propped ourselves up behind a bolder. We tried to spot Colin but couldn&#8217;t see him anymore, I shut my eyes for a second and dozed off. The next thing I remember was Colin arriving, agreeing to meet us at the other side of Binnein Beag. Once back to my feet after my sleep I felt sick. My legs still felt fine but I had a lack of energy, but walked around to where we hoped Colin would descend. Thankfully Phil produced some cake from his pack which he gave me, it was obvious I just needed some fuel. I don&#8217;t normally eat very much when I walk but with the heat and ascent I&#8217;d munched through everything I had taken with me except for one dehydrated meal. This clearly wasn&#8217;t enough food, the list below is the food I had on the trip which includes other food Phil handed out earlier in the day. I think he was just trying to lighten his pack but I&#8217;m glad he was.</p>

<p> <strong>Food:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>5 x Chocolate Chip Clif Bar</li>
<li>3 x Honey Stinger Bar</li>
<li>2 x Cadburys Brunch Bars</li>
<li>1 x Mars Bars</li>
<li>2 x Peperami</li>
<li>1 x <a href="https://www.fuizionfreezedriedfood.com/productitem.aspx?prodid=5c3d4675-fa06-4fb7-bec5-66710f5cd8fe">Fuizion Lamb Stew with Pearl Barley</a></li>
<li>1 x Squeeze Energy gum sweets (packet)</li>
</ul>


<p> <strong>From Phil:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>1 x Apple Slice</li>
<li>1 x Coop Cake</li>
<li>1 x Brioche</li>
</ul>


<p> <strong>Unused</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>1 x Mince Hotpot</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-099.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Once I had eaten the donated cake it was as if my batteries were restored. This was probably helped knowing that we only had descent remaining, if another Munro lay before us I imagine the energy would quickly recede. Colin eventually found us and we began the very boggy descent towards the Water of Nevis. I eventually gave up trying to find a dry line downwards and just headed as direct as I could. I was soon stood in the middle of Water of Nevis with a big smile on my face enjoying cool water flowing over my feet. Colin and Phil soon had the same look on their faces. The end was almost in site in my mind, we crossed Tom a&#8217; Choinneachaidh which is a very boggy area, where in wetter weather I can imagine sinking up to the waist in peat. Once we reached the path it was given a new name which would be inappropriate for children to read but it basically means its not very good. My Forerunners GPS batteries finally gave up, just as mine were now restored. It said we had already done 21 miles over the 2 days, Colin more. This doesn&#8217;t sound very much but with the ascent and the heat it felt much further.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Mamores-July-2011-100.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We still had 3 miles to the cars, but these flew by thinking about food. We passed a small waterfall with Phil asking if it was An Steall, the waterfall was probably only about 10 feet high. He would soon see the massive falls which as always looked stunning, this time in the evening light. Several people were passed setting up tents, it looked like about 10 people were trying to stop in a 3 or 4 man tent. By now we were in Road Runner mode with the road reached and the thought of food in all our minds. It had been a fantastic trip with superb weather and company. The trip was finished off with a Nevis burger each in the Glen Nevis Inn before we all headed our separate ways home. In my case a 5.5 hour journey, arriving home at 3am.</p>

<p>This was one of those rare trips where everything just slotted together, I can&#8217;t wait for the next and wish Colin all the best on his Colorado Trail.</p>

<p>There are lots of lessons from this trip the largest being the volume of food consumed, far more than I was expecting. I still had a full meal which would of been sufficient but when walking with others you don&#8217;t really want to hold everyone up by stopping to cook. I was quite surprised how much energy I had after the cake, thanks for that Phil. This will likely be the last time I write such a detailed report.</p>

<iframe src="http://new.socialhiking.org.uk/tracks/iframe/stevenhorner/The-Mamores" width="600" height="400"></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
