<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thinking | StevenHorner.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/categories/thinking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-25T16:54:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Horner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Focus, Fun and Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/18/focus-fun-and-learning/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-18T21:04:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/18/focus-fun-and-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm not setting resolutions for 2012, the plan for the year can be summed up with:</p>

<blockquote><p>Focus, Fun and Learning</p></blockquote>

<p>Rather than blathering on, I am going to try to keep my posts short (lightweight) as much as possible this year. Sometime in the next couple of months you will see some changes on this site, but for now that's all I'm saying.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>Planned trips/activities </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Scotland Winter Walking (February)</li>
<li>Run (March) - I have entered a short offroad race</li>
<li>Walking Skye (April)</li>
<li>Mountain Leader Training (May)</li>
<li>Relaxing Summer Holiday (June) - Maybe climb a mountain</li>
<li>UL Summer Summit (July/August)</li>
<li>Mountain Leader Assessment (September) - If enough experience</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Climbing</strong></p>

<p>Currently top roping indoors at around about 6b, intend to lead climb from February, then progress to rock outdoors in Spring/Summer.</p>

<p><strong>A few things I hope to learn more about:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Dry stone walling</li>
<li>Bushcraft &amp; wilderness skills</li>
<li>Geology Flora &amp; fauna</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Outdoor books on my 2012 reading list:</strong></p>

<p>*Disclaimer these are affiliate links</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0007424604/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0007424604">Ultimate Navigation Manual - Lyle Brotherton</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0007424604" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/071123180X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=071123180X">Granite and Grit: A Walker's Guide to the Geology of British Mountains - Ronald Turnbull</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=071123180X" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0954151100/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0954151100">Hill Walking: The Official Handbook of the Mountain Leader and Walking Group Leader Schemes</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0954151100" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/095415116X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=095415116X">Rock Climbing: Essential Skills &amp; Techniques (Mountain Leader Training Handb) - Libby Peter</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=095415116X" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0715328425/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0715328425">The Complete Guide to Climbing and Mountaineering - Pete Hill</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0715328425" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0954151135/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0954151135">Winter Skills: Essential Walking and Climbing Techniques</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0954151135" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0723251754/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0723251754">The Wild Flower Key (Revised Edition) - Francis Rose</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0723251754" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0007236859/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0007236859">Collins Complete Guide - British Trees: A photographic guide to every common species</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=0007236859" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1551051222/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1551051222">Bushcraft: Outdoor Skills and Wilderness Survival - Mors Kochanski</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=1551051222" alt="" /></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1905264941/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=1905264941">The Natural Navigator - Tristan Gooley</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=1905264941" alt="" />
I would recommend watching Alan Titchmarshs - <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B0002XOZQU/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=B0002XOZQU%22>British%20Isles&lt;/a>&lt;img%20src=%22http://www.assoc-amazon.co.uk/e/ir?t=faitocom-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=B0002XOZQU">British Isles: A Natural History</a> if you didn't see it on the BBC in 2004, excellent in conjunction with Ronald Turnbulls <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/071123180X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=071123180X">Granite and Grit</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2011  - Where did it go?]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/11/2011-where-did-it-go/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-11T10:30:40+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2012/01/11/2011-where-did-it-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://stevenhorner.github.com/pics/Mamores%20July%202011%20001.JPG" alt="" /></p>

<p>I wrote a long post looking back at 2011, reviewing gear, trips and all sorts of stuff. I decided to bin it though and instead the main things to take from the year were the excellent trips with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/philoutdoors">Phil</a>, <a href="www.twitter.com/tramplite">Colin</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/tookiebunten">Tookie</a>, my dad &amp; of course <a href="http://www.twitter.com/traci_howarth">Traci</a>:</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1540">Cairngorms Everything but the kitchen sink</a></li>
<li>Cairngorms with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/philoutdoors">Phil</a>, <a href="www.twitter.com/tramplite">Colin</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.twitter.com/tookiebunten">Tookie</a> - <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1476">The Mamores </a></li>
<li>Ben Nevis via CMD</li>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1358">Ben Nevis in Winter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1568">Aonach Eagach</a></li>
<li>Bidean nam Bian</li>
</ul>


<p>All of those trips were with others, an exception to this would be my wander onto the <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1445">Black Cuillin</a> prior to the start of the <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1445">Highland ZigZag</a> which was stunning.</p>

<p>When it comes to gear, the most notable thing is the lack of it. During 2011 I barely bought any, yes I received a few free things to test before saying No to anymore. It can be hard not to spend your hard earned money on more gear, when everywhere you look you are being told how fantastic this, that or the other is but generally I resisted. Possibly the reason for this is my focus on my finances and my desire to become debt free, the key to this is <a href="http://www.youneedabudget.com/">YNAB</a> which I would highly recommend checking out.
<img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8143/7456924492_58237a8972_b.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2>What did I learn</h2>

<ul>
<li>I enjoy walking with others more than solo (which I do still enjoy).</li>
<li>I no longer want I.T. to be my main job and would like to work in the outdoors in some way.</li>
<li>I don't need that new shiny kit.</li>
<li>Lightweight backpacking philosophy can be transfered to the rest of my life (less stuff).</li>
<li>Enjoy yourself no matter what!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wanderer Returns]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/11/24/wanderer-returns/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-24T14:00:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/11/24/wanderer-returns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-September-2011-049.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Sometimes it can be good to take a break from things and reflect on life and check that the path you are on, is the one you really want to follow. The break on this site has been part of that process.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Several months ago I decided I would no longer review Outdoor gear, unless I had bought it with my own money. Shortly after this the whole bloggers reviewing gear conversation blew up on various sites. I commented on one site, but generally decided to keep out of the conversation and wait until things calmed down. My personal opinion is that you can do what you like, it's your site, but personally I would rather disclose if I was given something. The reason for stopping reviewing is nothing to do with the online discussion, it's purely personal. Reviewing gear isn't something that I enjoy and trying to think of something interesting to write feels far too much of a chore (the day job is enough work). That's not why I spend my time in the outdoors and in the online outdoor community. Having said that, I love to read about gear and find out what others think of it.</p>

<p>In the last week alone I have turned down 3 companies offering gear to review, several people thought I was nuts for saying No.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scarborough-10K.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>While the site may of been quiet, away from the online world, my life has been anything but sedentary. After an operation on my heart I decided to start running regularly again and entered an race for the first time in years. The <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=scarborough%2010k&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CDoQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.yorkshirecoast10k.co.uk%2F&amp;ei=xz3OTumOFobe8QPMloTGDw&amp;usg=AFQjCNGiDnstSHTWOhh7qznBWGAl7VGa4Q">Scarborough 10K</a> which somehow I persuaded Traci (Girlfriend) to enter and we successfully completed the course. I may not of been happy at my time but the main thing is that my heart appears to be fixed and I will now need to find another excuse for being rubbish.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111023_165854-600x450.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A couple of years ago I started bouldering at <a href="www.durhamclimbingcentre.co.uk/">Durham Climbing Centre</a>, but the stop start nature of it caused problems with the ticker. Now that everything is OK, I have been climbing at <a href="www.sunderlandwall.co.uk/">Sunderland Wall</a> for the last few months with <a href="http://jonathancraddock.com">Jonathan Craddock</a> and more recently <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/traci_howarth">Traci</a> too. I'm still not very good, but have managed to climb up to F6b+ top roping. The next stage is to learn Lead climbing, then progress to rock outdoors next year.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/IMG_20111113_131438.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> There hasn't been a lack of walking either, a couple of trips with <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/philoutdoors">Phil Turner</a> most recently an Epic couple of days in the Cairngorms which delighted us with inversions, Broken Spectres, 4000 feet summits and night walking. An earlier trip also included <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/tramplite">Colin Ibbotson</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/tookiebunten">Tookie Bunten</a> in the Cairngorms and a trio of Trailstars.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Cairngorms-September-2011-073.jpg" alt="" /> <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Aonach-Eagach-2011-045.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Somehow I have been fortunate enough to find someone who is nuts as me (<a href="http://twitter.com/#!/traci_howarth">Traci</a>) and is happy (so she says) to wander up mountains, climb walls, run and generally put up with me talking about the outdoors. Over the last few months I've dragged Traci up several mountains including Bidean nam Bian, Ben Nevis, Scafell Pike, Helvellyn, boggy hills in Weardale and last weekend across the Aonach Eagach. Before meeting me she'd never done anything like this.
 <img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Scotland-September-2011-047.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> Walking with others is something I really enjoy, while I love solitude at times too. It is a very different experience walking with more than just my Kuksa for company. The majority of memorable trips have been shared experiences. Over the years I have encouraged and taken walking many friends, often their first experience of walking and the outdoors. I love doing this and a natural progression is to work towards the <a href="http://www.mltuk.org/">Mountain Leader qualification</a> which I have now embarked on. Hopefully I will attend the training course in May next year, I have far more than the required 20 "Quality" mountain days needed. Several months later I will then need to pass the Assessment and then will be a Summer Mountain Leader (fingers crossed). I have a plan in place which will hopefully take me to where I want to be in a couple of years and for the first time, what I'm doing and where I'm going feels like the correct path.</p>

<p> So what is going to happen to this site? <br>
 Now that I have formally announced no more reviews I can focus on the things I enjoy again, writing about my experiences, skills learned and observations. I mentioned above that I have a plan for the next couple of years, so much so that I have almost all my holiday scheduled until March 2013. This includes the <a href="http://ultralightsummit.com/2011/10/31/the-polls-are-closed/">Ultralight Backpackers Summit</a> <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com">Hendrik Morkel</a> is organising in Slovenia next year (dates to be confirmed). These trips and my experiences <strong>will</strong> now be more regularly written up on here.</p>

<p> I have 2 other Outdoor related sites in the pipeline, both involve a lot of work but once there is something to show I will write about it here. Thanks to everyone I have walked with and spoken to online. I have returned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mind Games]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/01/01/mind-games/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-01T22:15:36+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2011/01/01/mind-games</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Munro-Week-August-2010-336.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
At the moment many are reflecting on 2010 and setting resolutions for 2011. An idea has been brewing for weeks to do a video review of 2010 that would cover the people, places and experiences of the year, It's a lot of work and I've had other things on my mind recently. I don't intend to set any resolutions as such; but may post my goals/aims for the year next week.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This post is sort of related to the above but more specifically reflecting on the last month, you may (or more likely not) have noticed that I've done very little walking in December.</p>

<p>The planned trip with <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/">Hendrik</a>, <a href="http://www.petesy.co.uk/">Petesy</a> and <a href="http://www.recipher.co.uk/">Johnny</a> was canceled due to airport and road closures but that was at the end of November and I then more or less disappeared from this site. I have written in the past about problems with my heart and specific events like my <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=1227">North Yorkshire 3 peaks</a> episode or <a href="http://www.stevenhorner.com/?p=972">C2C</a>. I have normally dealt with this by getting back up and pushing on immediately much like getting back on a horse, usually pushing harder than when the event happened.</p>

<p>I was scheduled to see a specialist in early December to discuss having an operation, which had been briefly mentioned for over 3 years. The appointment was rescheduled to the 30th December which has summed up my whole experience, constant cancellations and different doctors every trip. Between the cancellation of the original appointment and my new one I had several "episodes" which were far more frequent and lasted longer than the norm.</p>

<p>The NY 3 peaks "episode" was probably more worrying to me than I let on to anyone, quite early in the walk I more or less collapsed. I couldn't get back to my feet for a few minutes but I knew if I turned around and went back to the car I would be giving in. So on this occasion I eventually managed to get up and decided to carry on and rather than just walking the next 22 miles I decided to run much of the downhill.</p>

<p>After this I then had another "episode" cycling home from work and on this occasion I spent 45 minutes sat at the side of a busy road trying to slow my heart rate, unable to hold my bike upright. Eventually I decided I couldn't sit there any longer and phoned the cavalry (my parents). I almost immediately regretted the decision when my heart rate slowed and I then felt defeated.</p>

<p>The third "episode" I'd decided to walk the 1 mile in the snow to the local town for groceries but once I left the house I decided to run which always makes me smile. Half a mile later and I had to sit on a stile for 15 minutes while my heart went crazy. I pushed on a few hundreds yards more struggling to stand, let alone walk. I decided to prop myself against a wall near the main road and once again tried exercises to slow my heart rate. While doing this it started to snow heavily and 30 minutes later I looked like a snowman and was probably as cold as one. Luckily just when I was contemplating asking a tractor driver for a lift, my heart returned to normal and I carried on for the groceries (again not giving in).</p>

<p>The last incident must of had a bigger impact on me than I realised and it's only the last few days that I noticed I'd began making excuses not to go out walking. Previously it was rare that anything happened and usually not for very long but the frequency and duration has increased recently and for some reason I'd allowed doubt to creep into my mind. I knew that I wasn't going to die from any of these episode (unless I fall off a ridge) but I had for the first time allowed this seed into my mind. I'm not sure if this was because it coincided with a few weeks of tiredness and then flu but I became sluggish and very unlike the "me" of the last year.</p>

<p>Luckily I finally got to see the specialist a couple of days ago and its the first time I've felt positive after any discussion relating to my heart. When a doctor says "You will not die from this" its always reassuring and he went through everything, what was happening and what he was intending to do. He agreed with everything I'd previously concluded regarding medication (shouldn't take any) and I will be having the procedure once I receive a date; hopefully in about 3 months.</p>

<p>I'm not going to get into what the procedure entails on here, but afterwards I should be normal (me normal?) and the day after can do whatever I like, climb Everest maybe?</p>

<p>I feel back to myself and that seed of doubt has gone, yeah I will no doubt have a few "episodes" until the operation but I can live with them as I have been. The majority of challenges in life are mental, staying positive and believing in yourself is the biggest battle.</p>

<p>The catalyst for the state of mind change probably wasn't just the doctor or the new year but being awoken this morning (January 1st) by a butterfly flapping its wings against my bedroom blind. Maybe I was half asleep, hungover or have talked with <a href="http://helenswonderings.blogspot.com/">Helen</a> too much but it felt like it signified a change and a new start.</p>

<p>I will be out walking tomorrow!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deafening Silence]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2010/12/02/deafening-silence/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-02T19:29:48+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenhorner.github.com/blog/2010/12/02/deafening-silence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Ben-Lomond-November-2010-134.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
Its been eerily quiet on this blog recently, much like the current blanket of snow has made the whole world appear silent and desolate this has been reflected here.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In reality I've just been busy, walks up Ben Lomond, Helvellyn and an aborted trip to Scotland with <a href="hikinginfinland.com">Hendrik</a>, <a href="http://www.petesy.co.uk/">Petesy</a> and <a href="http://www.recipher.co.uk/">Johnny Hall </a>have kept me occupied.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Snow-December-2010-034.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
So what's happening, I've been using and testing several bits of gear that I have bought over recent weeks and months and intend to actually write about, among them are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.terra-nova.co.uk/Product_Type/Lightweight_Packs/Laser_20L_Pack.html">Terra Nova Laser 20L</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.inov-8.com/Products-Detail.asp?PG=PG1&amp;L=26&amp;P=5050973079">Inov-8 Oroc 340s</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.pogu.co.uk/">Pogu Spikes</a> <a href="http://www.theomm.com/products/packs/classicMarathon32L.html">OMM Classic 32L</a> (everyone has one of these!)</li>
</ul>


<p>There are a few other things on their way like mittens and a <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B002LVUWFE?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faitocom-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=B002LVUWFE">Kindle</a> that will also feature in future posts.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Helvellyn-Ridge-November-2010-058.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
I may also write up the trips to <a href="http://helenswonderings.blogspot.com/2010/11/not-lake-district.html">Ben Lomond</a> &amp; Helvellyn although Helen has done a <a href="http://helenswonderings.blogspot.com/2010/11/not-lake-district.html">better job</a> than I would manage with the former.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Ben-Lomond-November-2010-128.jpg" alt="" /><br/>
Plans for the future are forming with not getting a place in the 2011 TGO Challenge I did feel slightly left out with so many bloggers claiming places, but I hope to do something a bit different. The only thing that I'm going to mention at this stage is a Sutherland Peaks walk I've been pondering for months that I have to route plan &amp; schedule.</p>

<p>I also feel slightly guilty this year neglecting County Durham (where I live) so I intend to rectify this by walking a series of routes throughout the County and hope it may entice a few more people to walk here. This I hope to be more than just trip reports, but guides to walking each route that could be downloaded and of course GPX files for each.</p>

<p>There have been discussions on Twitter with a certain <a href="http://lightweightoutdoors.com/">Mr T</a> about a longer trail but his plans are up in the air and I NEED something special next year, suggestions in the comments please (no longer than 6 weeks preferably 2-4 weeks).</p>

<p>This post is basically just to let people know I'm still alive and what to expect in the near future. Oh I will be doing plenty of walking in all this snow!!<br/>
<img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/2657852/website/images/Snow-December-2010-037.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
